<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A confutation of the Dutch-Arminian tenent of universal redemption with relation in special unto certain sectaries in England : by name, the Morians or Revelators, with others tracing them, who hold that Christ died for all men, good and bad / by Theoph. Brabourne.</title>
            <author>Brabourne, Theophilus, b. 1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37451</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16958768</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16958768</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105460</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105460)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1610:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A confutation of the Dutch-Arminian tenent of universal redemption with relation in special unto certain sectaries in England : by name, the Morians or Revelators, with others tracing them, who hold that Christ died for all men, good and bad / by Theoph. Brabourne.</title>
                  <author>Brabourne, Theophilus, b. 1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Will. Bentley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Particularism (Theology)</term>
               <term>Arminianism --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105460:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONFUTATION of the <hi>DUTCH</hi>-ARMINIAN <hi>TENENT,</hi> of <hi>Univerſal Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Relation in ſpecial, unto certain Sectaries, in ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>By name, the <hi>Morians,</hi> or <hi>Revelators,</hi> with others tracing them; who hold, <hi>That Chriſt died for all men, good and bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THEOPH. BRABOURN.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 7.6.</hi>
               </bibl> Give ye not that which is holy, to dogs; neither caſt ye your pearls, before ſwine.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by WILL. BENTLEY, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105460:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105460:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cource (Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader) lying by me, and fitted for the Preſs; but with thoughts, never to have it Printed ſo long as I live: my mind is now altered, very lately, upon this occation: Finding by ſad experience, that this <hi>Dutch-ARMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIAN Tenent,</hi> of <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Redemption,</hi> hath of
<pb facs="tcp:105460:3"/> late invaded our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and infected the minds, and perverted the judgement of many, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend higheſt for God and godlineſs; I could not but alter my thoughts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to publiſh this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cource, if it may be, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the further growth and ſpreading of it. There is a Sect of <hi>Revelators,</hi> or <hi>Manifeſtators,</hi> called <hi>Mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> of one <hi>MORE</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling near <hi>Wisbech,</hi> who with his Diſciples, about eight or nine years ſince, were orthodox in this point with us; but ſince, finding this <hi>new light,</hi> of <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Redemption,</hi> to be a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:105460:3"/> means to further an other and more ancient <hi>new light,</hi> which formerly he had received and taught; namely, his doctrine of <hi>Free-grace,</hi> as he calls it, preſently he ſet abroach this <hi>Univerſal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> among his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: of and from whom (as I ſuppoſe) our <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents</hi> of later time, have borrowed this light: for of late, ſome of them are not aſhamed to teach and preach it publickly, offering Chriſt and the benefits of his death, to <hi>dogs</hi> and <hi>ſwine,</hi> to the worſt of men, ſaying, Come <hi>Whoremaſter,</hi> come <hi>Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> the work is wrought for you, believe it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and they
<pb facs="tcp:105460:4"/> may as well ſay, Come <hi>Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> come <hi>Rogue,</hi> come Tag and Rag, believe it, Chriſt died for you all. Thus they fear not, to give <hi>Chriſt</hi> that <hi>Pearl</hi> and <hi>Holy thing,</hi> unto dogs and ſwine. Their new <hi>Arminian</hi> light hath taught them, to give the <hi>Childrens bread</hi> to dogs. Not long ſince, ſome of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were tainted with this Error, and how odious were they for it in the eyes of theſe very men? but now themſelves are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the ſame Error, and it is become a lovely Truth: and what have theſe men to ſay for this Error more than the <hi>Biſhops</hi> had? ſurely, if ſo much, yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:105460:4"/> more, unleſs it be this, that it is a bright beam of <hi>new light</hi> ariſen to them of late; and notably tending to <hi>their</hi> new doctrine of <hi>Free grace,</hi> as they call it; and that the <hi>ſpirit</hi> hath taught it them: but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that there is a <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> and a <hi>ſpirit of Error, 1.</hi> John <hi>4.6.</hi> and ſo I end.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THEO. BRABOURN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:105460:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105460:5"/>
            <head>A CONFUTATION of the ARMINIAN Tenent, of <hi>Univerſal Redemption.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N handling this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, I ſhall firſt propound ſundrie Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt it. Secondly, I ſhall make anſwer unto the Texts alleadged by Arminians, for proof of their Tenent. Thirdly, I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute a common Anſwer of theirs, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a notable Objection of ours. And Fourthly, I ſhall confute their diſtinction of Impetration and Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. I begin with the firſt of theſe: and theſe are my Arguments againſt it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105460:6"/>
               <head>ARGUM. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If Chriſt forbade his ministers, to give, or deliver his Word and Sacrament concerning his death, unto all men, as unto unbelieving, impenitent, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and wicked men; Then Christ did not give or deliver himſelf to death for all men: or, then Chriſt died not for all men.</hi> The reaſon hereof is this; If Chriſt had given himſelf to death for all men, good and bad, then would he have his miniſters to do ſo too, in delivering the Word and Sacrament; and it is againſt reaſon to think, that Chriſt ſhould give himſelf for all men, and forbid his miniſters to give him to all men, or to ſome men: ſo there is the ſame reaſon of both: Now if he forbade his miniſters, to deliver his Word and Sacrament unto all men, unto wicked and impenitent men, then ſurely, he did not deliver himſelf to death for all men.</p>
               <p>For 1. It is abſurd to think, that a miniſters <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> in delivering the Word and Sacrament concerning Chriſts death, ſhould be of leſs extent than Chriſt his death is of; as, that his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion ſhould extend but to ſome men onely, when Chriſt his death ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105460:6"/> to all men: wherefore if his Commiſſion be but unto ſome men onely, then Chriſt his death is not to, or for all men, but to and for ſome men onely. 2. The Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament concerning Chriſt his death, are <hi>ſigns</hi> repreſenting Chriſts death unto us; now the ſign and the thing ſignified by it, muſt be of equal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; as, if the ſign belong but unto ſome men onely, then Chriſt his death, the thing ſignified by it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not unto all men, but unto ſome men onely. 3. If Chriſt would not permit his miniſters, to give the <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>wine</hi> in the Sacrament (which is the leſſer) unto all men, then much leſs would he give himſelf which is the greater) unto all men: If he forbade his miniſters, to give his bread and wine unto all men, much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs would he give his life, his own bodie and bloud for all men: if he denied the <hi>Sign</hi> unto wicked and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent perſons, then much more would he denie there the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, which is, his pretious bodie and bloud: ſo much for my propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But Chriſt forbade his miniſters, to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105460:7"/> give, or deliver his Word and Sacrament concerning his death unto all men, as unto unbelieving, impenitent, ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and wicked men.</hi> This my aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption I thus prove, firſt concerning the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. It is the doctrine, both of our own and other reformed Churches, that Chriſt would not have the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Lords ſupper,</hi> given by the miniſter unto unbelievers, impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſcandalous, and wicked men. 2. <hi>Philip</hi> would not give the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſm unto the Eunuch, but upon the condition of his faith firſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. S. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have the Lords ſupper given unto the inceſtuous perſon, 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5.1, 5, 13. nor unto impenitent wicked men, as not unto fornicatours, idolaters, drunkards, railers, nor extortioners, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. and ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. So much for the Sacrament, next for the <hi>Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Concerning the <hi>Word:</hi> Chriſt would not have the word concerning his death, given or delivered by his miniſters unto unbelievers, impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſcandalous, and wicked men; which I thus prove:</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105460:7"/>
               <p>In the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> delivers the bread, with theſe <hi>words</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>This is my bodie, which is broken for thee:</hi> the which words, are according to Chriſts inſtitution, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19. now foraſmuch as Chriſt would not have impenitent wicked perſons admitted to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he would not have his miniſters deliver unto them, this his <hi>word</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his death, This is my bodie: which <hi>is broken for thee:</hi> ſo Chriſts mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter may not ſay to a wicked man, Chriſt died for thee. Yet if Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans doctrine be true, that Chriſt died for all men, then a miniſter may ſay to the vileſt impenitent perſon, were he a <hi>Judas</hi> or worſe, Chriſt died for thee. And by the way, I wonder that <hi>Independents</hi> can hold forth Chriſt to all men in a Sermon, ſaying, Come whore-maſter, drunkard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chriſt died for thee; and yet refuſe to give the Lords ſupper to ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſaying to them; Chriſt died for thee. 2. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> would not have <hi>holy things given to dogs,</hi> nor <hi>pearls to ſwine,</hi> Matth. 7.6. now wicked and impenitent perſons, appearing incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105460:8"/> are dogs and ſwine; &amp; Chriſt, whether given in the <hi>word</hi> or in the <hi>ſacrament,</hi> is an holy thing, and a pearl: wherefore a miniſter may not give Chriſt to an incorrigible wicked man, ſaying, Chriſt died for thee. 3. S. <hi>Paul</hi> preached the <hi>word</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſts death at <hi>Antioch,</hi> Acts 13.14, 16, 27, 38. where being a mixt multitude, of ſheep and goats, of wheat and tares, he directs his ſpeech unto the ſheep and wheat, not unto the goats and tares; for he ſpake as he ſaid, <hi>To thoſe that fear God,</hi> Acts 13.16, 26. and ſo ſoon as ſome of his Auditours appeared to be goats and tares, and ſuch as feared not God, he turned away from them, and carried away the Goſpel unto the Gentiles, refuſing to preach the word of Chriſt unto them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45, 46. and ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 19.9. whereby you ſee, S. <hi>Paul</hi> a miniſter of Chriſt, would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the <hi>word</hi> concerning Chriſts death, unto wicked men, and ſuch as feared not God.</p>
               <p>It may be objected, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>It was neceſſarie,</hi> that this <hi>word ſhould firſt be preached unto them,</hi> that is, unto thoſe goats and tares, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105460:8"/> Jews <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> preached of Chriſts death, as well to wicked men as to the godly. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I anſwer, 1. As the Husband-man beſtoweth the ſame pains, upon the tares as upon the wheat, before the tares appear to him to be tares; ſo the Apoſtle might preach Chriſt to the wicked, as well as to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they being together in a mixt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, before the wicked appeared to him to be wicked: but yet as the husband-man takes pains for the wheats ſake, and not for the tares ſake; ſo <hi>Paul</hi> might preach Chriſt, for the godly's ſake, and not for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked's ſake: and it is evident in the Text to be ſo: for <hi>Paul</hi> directs his ſpeech unto the godly in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to thoſe that <hi>feared God, Acts</hi> 13.16.26. excluding the wicked: for when in an Aſſembly, there are both godly and wicked, if the miniſter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects his ſpeech to the godly, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the wicked; or if he directs an uſe to the wicked, he excludes the godly. 2. So ſoon as theſe tares, the obſtinate Jews, appeared to <hi>Paul</hi> to be tares, as you ſee, he refuſed to preach Chriſt unto them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105460:9"/> 46. and for the ſame cauſe, had he known them at the firſt to be tares, and if he could have ſeparated them from the aſſembly of the godly, he would not have preached Chriſt unto them at the firſt. True it is, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, It was <hi>neceſſarie</hi> that the Word ſhould be preached vnto them: for it could not be avoided, being they were mixed with the godly, and did not at firſt appear to be tares: it was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſarie for <hi>Paul</hi> to preach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, with the godly at the firſt, though he intended not his doctrine to be for them. Thus I have proved my Aſſumption: and ſo the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on follows thus,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore Chriſt did not give or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver himſelf to death for all men: or, Chriſt died not for all men.</hi> So much for my firſt Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If Chriſt would not pray for all men, then Chriſt would not die for all men.</hi> The reaſon thereof is this; If Chriſt would not do the leſſer for all men, then he would not do the greater for all men: If Chriſt would not offer to God, the <hi>calves</hi> of his lips for all men,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105460:9"/> then he would not offer to God the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> of his pretious bodie and bloud for all men: If Chriſt would not beſtow ſo much <hi>love</hi> upon all men as to pray for them, then would he not beſtow ſo much love upon all men as to die, and to ſhed his heart bloud for them: In a word, If Chriſt would exclude ſome men from his prayers, ſurely he meant to exclude them from his bitter death and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So much for my propoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But Chriſt would not pray for all men.</hi> For proof hereof ſee <hi>John</hi> 17.8, 9. where believers are diſtinguiſhed from the world, that is, from the world of unbelievers; and for theſe men who then did believe, Chriſt prayed, ſaying, <hi>I pray for them,</hi> verſ. 9. and Chriſt prayed alſo for thoſe men, who ſhould afterwards to the worlds end believe in him <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. but for the world, that is, for the world of unbelievers, Chriſt would not vouchſafe ſo much as to pray to God for them, ſaying, <hi>I pray not for the world,</hi> verſ. 9. So much for proof of my Aſſumption, and ſo my Concluſion follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore Chriſt would not die for all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105460:10"/> men.</hi> And by conſequence, <hi>Chriſt did not die for all men:</hi> for look what Chriſt would not do, that he did not do: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we ſhould imagine, that Chriſt his will, and his actions, were contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to the other: or, that he did do that, which he did not firſt will to do.</p>
               <p>Arminians in their <hi>Acta Synodalia, de Morte Chriſti,</hi> pag. 319. do anſwer to my Aſſumption, and to my Text brought to prove it, thus; Chriſt ſaith not, that he <hi>would</hi> not pray for the world, that is, that he would never af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards pray for them; but thus he ſaith, that he <hi>doth</hi> not pray for the world, that is, that he doth not for that preſent time pray for them; or that he doth not in this particular prayer, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. pray for them. Hereunto I thus reply.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though I ſhall prove by and by, that there is more in Chriſts words, than Arminians do grant, yet this which they do grant, is ſufficient to make good my argument: for this is in the Text, and they grant it, that Chriſt ſaid, He <hi>did</hi> not pray for the world, that is, at that time and in that particular prayer, he did not pray
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105460:10"/> for them: from which it doth unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably follow, that as he <hi>did</hi> not then pray for them, ſo he <hi>would</hi> not <hi>then</hi> pray for them; or it was his will, at that time and in that prayer, not to pray for them, but to exclude them from his prayer, and from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereof. This I thus make good.</p>
               <p>A wiſe mans actions and words, do flow from his underſtanding and his will; and his words and deeds, are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated and governed by his will; ſo as what he doth or ſpeaketh, the ſame he firſt willed; and what he refuſeth to do or to ſpeak, the ſame he willeth, or willeth not to do or ſpeak, I ſay, being a mans actions and words are regulated by his will, both in his ſpeech, and in his ſilence refuſing to ſpeak, whenſoever, he is ſo ſilent, as that he refuſeth to ſpeak, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that it is his <hi>will</hi> to be ſilent, and to refuſe to ſpeak: wherefore when Chriſt ſaid, I pray not, or I do not now in this prayer pray for the world; hereby it is evident, that at that time his will, was not to pray for them; but that his will was againſt it, or his will was againſt praying for them at that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105460:11"/> time: becauſe he willed ſilence at this time, and refuſed to pray for them in this prayer.</p>
               <p>When a father having ten ſons, ſaith, I give unto my nine elder ſons, an hundred pounds apeece, but is ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſaying nothing of his tenth or youngeſt ſon; ſuppoſe it will not hence follow, that the fathers mind and will was to denie him, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to give him an hundred pounds; yet it is otherwiſe in this caſe: for when the father ſaith, I give an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds apeece to my nine elder ſons, but as for my tenth and young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſon, who is a wicked man, a riotous and prodigal ſon, I give him nothing; here it is manifeſt, that the fathers <hi>will</hi> was, to exclude the youngeſt ſon, and to be unwilling at that time that he ſhould have an hundred pounds: ſo our Saviour, having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good and godly followers of him, who were believers, ſaith, I pray for them <hi>John</hi> 17.9. and for all them, <hi>John</hi> 17.20. but as for the world, that is, for impenitent and unbelieving men, I pray not for them, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. here it is clear, that as he did not then pray for them, ſo he would not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105460:11"/> at that time pray for them: for he vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily excluded them from his prayer, when he prayed for others.</p>
               <p>Such negative ſpeeches as this in <hi>John</hi> 17.9. are voluntary denials, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſals, or excluſions; not onely ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying a thing not done, but alſo a will not to do it, as you may ſee <hi>John</hi> 8.11, 50. and 13.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.2.</p>
               <p>Thus it is proved, that as Chriſt did not in that prayer pray for the world, ſo it was not his will but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, then to pray for them: now hence it followeth, That if at any time Chriſt did voluntarily refuſe to pray for any men, then he would not die for them, or then he would refuſe to die for them: and ſo you ſee, that from what Arminians do grant, my argument is made good: but I ſhall further prove, more to be in Chriſts words, than what they grant, and thus I prove it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As Chriſt did not pray for the world, and alſo as is proved, Chriſt would not at that time and in that prayer pray for them; ſo it is gathera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from the Text and context, that Chriſt would never afterwards pray for them; the which Arminians deny,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105460:12"/> and this I here prove: Chriſt his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though uttered and made then, yet the virtue and extent of it laſted after, or unto the death of that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world of impenitent wicked men: for as Chriſts prayer, once made for the godly, extends it ſelf for their good, unto their death, <hi>John</hi> 17.9, 11, 15, 21, 24. ſo Chriſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of that wicked world, from the benefit of his prayer once, muſt be an excluſion of them for ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: unleſs it could be ſhown, that after Chriſts prayer, that wicked world converted and believed, which cannot be ſhown. Now if this wicked world were ever after the ſame, why ſhould Chriſt alter his mind towards them? why ſhould he pray for them afterwards, more than he did before? and I can but marvel, that Arminians ſhould grant, that once Chriſt <hi>did</hi> not pray for that world, and yet ſuppoſe that afterwards he did pray for them; and yet have no ground for this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed thing.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The ground and reaſon of Chriſt his prayer, will clear it up, that as he did not for the preſent pray for the world, ſo he <hi>would</hi> not for the future
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105460:12"/> pray for them; or ſo he would never after pray for them. The reaſon why Chriſt prayed for believers, was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>believed in him,</hi> John 17.8, 9, 20. and becauſe they were Gods people, <hi>for they are thine,</hi> John 17.9. and becauſe God the Father had <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to Chriſt,</hi> John 17.9. On the contrary, the reaſon why Chriſt prayed not for the world, muſt needs be, becauſe they were worldlings, wicked and impenitent perſons, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, and were none of Gods people, nor given to Chriſt: now this being the <hi>cauſe,</hi> why Chriſt refuſed to pray for them at that preſent time, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. for the <hi>ſame cauſe,</hi> Chriſt could never pray for them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: for many of that wicked world, lived and died impenitently, and in unbelief, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. <hi>John</hi> 3.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45, 46, 50. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41, 42. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.27, 31, 32. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.14, 15. <hi>Mark</hi> 4.11, 12. If their unbelief hindered Chriſts prayer at that time, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. it muſt for ever after hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his prayer: becauſe many of them were ever after unbelievers, and the very ſame men as before, when Chriſt refuſed to pray for them.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105460:13"/> So much for my ſecond Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If Christ ſo loved all men, as to give himſelf and die for all men; then would he have cauſed the Goſpel to be preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all men; by means whereof, they ſhould have knowledge of his death, and might believe in him, ſo as to be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his death.</hi> This I thus prove.</p>
               <p n="1">1 He that willeth the End, he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the means tending unto it, and whereby it muſt be obtained: the end and the proper or neceſſary means cannot be ſeparated: Chriſts death for men, is the End, the preaching of Chriſts death in the Goſpel, is the means for men to know it, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, ſo as to be the better for it: wherefore, if Chriſt ſo loved all men, as to die and give himſelf for them, he could not but out of the ſame his love, have given them know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it by preaching, which is the means of faith, that ſo they might partake of the benefit of his death.</p>
               <p n="2">2 If Chriſt out of his love <hi>John</hi> 3.16. and 15.13. died for all men, then if he would not give all men know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105460:13"/> of it, whereby they might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to themſelves, or believe in him, that ſo they might be the better for his death; then he is like a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, pretending the greateſt love poſſible to cure his friend, by prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and making a moſt ſoveraign po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him; but ſets it behind or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bed, or in ſome ſecret corner of the chamber, where it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the ſick man to find it: all this is but a pretence of love: for if it were true love, he would have ſet it where the ſick man ſhould have had knowledge of it, or he would have given him knowledge of it, that ſo he might make uſe of it for his health: ſo if Chriſt had died for all men, all men ſhould have known it, and muſt have had it preached unto them, that ſo they might make uſe of it for ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="3">3 They may as well ſay, God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth by ordinary means, to ſave a mans natural life, and yet denie him food, as to ſay, Chriſt intended to die for the ſalvation of all men, and yet denie them the knowledge of it by the Goſpel preached. So much for my Major.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105460:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But Chriſt neither would nor hath cauſed the Goſpel to be preached to all men; whereby they ſhould be brought to faith, and be the better for his death.</hi> This I thus prove, 1. The Goſpel is not in theſe days preached to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Indians,</hi> and barbarous nations. 2. In old time before us, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, or any thing of Chriſt, was not preached to millions of Gentiles, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.12, 28. and 16.6, 7. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. 3. Chriſt preached to ſome men in parables, and darkly, to this end, that they ſhould not obtain remiſſion of ſins, and be the better for his death, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.11, 12. So much for my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor; and the concluſion follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore Chriſt did not ſo love all men, as to give himſelf, and to die for all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I have done with this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, I muſt anſwer an Objection, which my Reader may make; and confute an Anſwer, which the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> do make: the Objection is this you ſaid in your firſt Argument, that Chriſt would not have the word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his death (which is Goſpel) to be preached to wicked, impenitent,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105460:14"/> and unbelieving men: and here in this third Argument, you ſay, that the Goſpel ought to be preached to all men; and among all men, are many wicked men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hereunto I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that this is no contradiction: for in my firſt Argument, I ſpake abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and as the truth is; but here in my third Argument, I ſpeak not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, but conditionally, with an <hi>if:</hi> as, If Chriſt died for all men, then the Goſpel muſt be preached to all men, be they godly or wicked: ſo this I ſpeak but upon a ſuppoſition of the truth of the Arminian tenent, which if it be true, then this follows, that Goſpel muſt be preached to all men, good and bad. So much of this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection: and now I come to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of Arminians, which is this.</p>
               <p>The Arminians in their <hi>Acta Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalia, de Morte Chriſti,</hi> pag. 327, 328. do anſwer this my third Argument thus: that a limitation is to be added to my Major, and then my Minor will be falſe: thus therefore they frame it a new, and limit it: <hi>If Chriſt ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all men, as to die for all men; then would he have cauſed the Goſpel to be actually preached to all men; or elſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105460:15"/> be prepared and in a readineſſe to have it preached, ſo ſoon as men be fitted to receive it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The better to colour this limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they make a twofold calling, a common or general calling, and a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial calling: by the general calling, they underſtand the law and light of nature, as the natural knowledge that there is a God, and of the law of God, to which men ow obedience: now to him that uſeth this aright, God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to communicate unto him his ſpecial calling, which is, the preaching of the Goſpel: ſo the well uſing of that, is a fitting and preparing of men for this: and the reaſon why many men are denied the Goſpel, is their own fault, becauſe they do abuſe the light of nature, or the general calling: ſo then Gods will is, to have the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel preached actually to all men that are fitted for it; and is <hi>prepared</hi> to have it preached to others, ſo ſoon as they be fitted for it, and ſo be they do not put a <hi>bar</hi> in the way to hinder God, by their evil deſerts, and unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</p>
               <p>Hereunto I thus reply, I will not contend about this order and method
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105460:15"/> of God, that firſt he willeth all men, to make good uſe of the law and light of nature; and then and not before to vouchſafe the Goſpel to them; be this true or falſe, I will not queſtion it, but rather grant it for argument ſake: but yet this I denie, (though it be never ſo true in it ſelf) that this limitation ſhall be added to my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, <hi>That God is prepared to have the Goſpel preached to men, ſo ſoon as men be fitted for it and not before;</hi> for this is an abſurd limitation: and it is to maintain one Errour by another, the which I make thus appear,</p>
               <p n="1">1 They ſay, as it is, implied in the antecedent part of my Major, That Chriſt died for all men: and then they would add to it this, That ſome of thoſe men are not fit to know it, or not fitted to hear of it and receive it (for this is implied in their limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:) now is not this an abſurd thing to be added? as firſt to hold, that Chriſt died for all men, and then to add to this, that ſome of thoſe men are not fit to hear of it, or to know it? This wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>erable, if it were held, that though men be unfit to know it at ſome one time of their lives,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105460:16"/> yet they ſhould be fit at ſome other time before death; but foraſmuch as men abuſe the light of nature all their lives long, and ſo die impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently, therefore they muſt hold, that many men are never fit, to hear of or know, what Chriſt hath done for them: and is it not abſurd to ſay, Chriſt died for many men, who nor are, nor ever ſhall be fit to know it? or Chriſt died for many, who ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be fit to know what he hath done for them? are they fitted for Chriſt to die for them, and not fitted to know he died for them?</p>
               <p>This conceit is like unto this; A man pays a ranſom, to redeem one from captivitie or priſon, but the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner or captive is not fit to hear or know of it, ſo long as he liveth: or like unto this, A Phyſitian, makes an excellent and healthfull potion or cordial for his ſick patient, but adds this, ſaying, He ſhall know of it ſo ſoon as he is fit to know of it and to receive it, when as he knows the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſhall never be fit ſo long as he lives; is not this abſurd: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>refore, if they will hold, that Chriſt died for all men, they muſt hold alſo, that they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105460:16"/> are fit to know and hear of it: which being ſo, this is a frivolous and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd limitation, to add ſaying, or elſe God and Chriſt be <hi>prepared,</hi> to cauſe the Goſpel to be preached to men, ſo ſoon as they be <hi>fitted</hi> for it, or be fit to receive it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Chriſt foreſaw, that many men in the world, would never make a good uſe of the law and light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whereby to be fitted to know of his death. If therefore this was no hinderance for Chriſt to die for them, then this is no hinderance for the Goſpel to be preached to them: for there is as good reaſon for the one as the other: yea the reaſon is ſtronger, to think mens unfitneſs ſhould rather hinder Chriſt to die for them, than to hinder a ſermon of Chriſts death to be preached to them: for Chriſt his bloud is of more value, than a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters words and breath: wherefore, if Chriſt died for all men, then are all men fit to hear of it: and ſo this limitation of <hi>fitneſs</hi> is frivolous.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, thoſe whom Chriſt died for, thoſe he loved infinitely, and unſpeakably, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. and 15.13. now if it be true, as Arminians
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105460:17"/> ſay, that Chriſt died for all men, then he infinitely and unſpeakably loved all men, even thoſe who abuſed the general call, <hi>the light of nature,</hi> albeit he foreſaw they would live and die in in the abuſe of it: and was his love ſo hot and ſtrong to thoſe men, as to paſs by this abuſe, when he ſhed his hearts bloud for them; and was it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo cold and weak to them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as to ſtick at it and not paſs it by, when he thought of cauſing a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of his death to be preached to them, whereby they might be the better for his death? was Chriſts love ſo hot, as to require no fitneſs in them, when he died for them, and was it become ſo cold afterward, as to ſtick at theſe mens unfitneſs to hear a ſermon of his death? ſurely, if nothing in theſe men, could hinder Chriſt to die for them; then nothing in them, can hinder a ſermon of Chriſt to be preached to them: if there needed no qualification in them, to render them fit for Chriſt to die for them; then there needs no qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in them, to fit them to hear a ſermon of Chriſt: unleſs you ſuppoſe more virtue or dignitie to be in a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105460:17"/> ſermon of Chriſt, than is in the bloud of Chriſt: ſo you ſee, this limitation of fitneſs is vain.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To ſay, Chriſt died for all men; and then to add this unto it, That they ſhall not have the Goſpel (which is a neceſſary means of obtaining the end of Chriſts death) preached unto them, unleſs they be fit for it, or untill they be fitted to receive it, is a very abſurd addition and limitation as you have ſeen: ſo it is alſo as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, to ſay, God or Chriſt is <hi>prepared</hi> and in a <hi>readineſs,</hi> to have the Goſpel preached ſo ſoon as men be fitted for it: for there be thouſands of <hi>Indians</hi> and others, who live and die in the abuſe of the law and light of nature, and ſo are never fit for the Goſpel, and who never heard the Goſpel: now can it be truly ſaid, that God or Chriſt hath <hi>prepared</hi> himſelf, to uſe and apply means unto ſuch, as never will be capable of the means? and unto ſuch, as he well knows and fore-ſees will never be capable of it? did ever any wiſe man <hi>prepare himſelf,</hi> to do any thing, the which he fore-ſees ſhall never be done? and yet ſuch a preparation Arminians do aſcribe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105460:18"/> the wiſe God. Will a Phyſitian <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare</hi> himſelf, to give phiſick to a dead man, or to one whom he knows will never be fit to take it?</p>
               <p>Moreover, If this fitneſs be pre-required, then thus I reaſon: God not onely fore-ſees that many will never be fit for the Goſpel, but alſo is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in himſelf, that the Goſpel ſhall never be preached to them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he fore-ſees, they ſhall and will live and die unfitted; now can it be ſaid, that God is <hi>prepared</hi> to do that thing, which he is <hi>reſolved</hi> in himſelf ſhall never be done? you may as well ſay, God is <hi>prepared</hi> to ſave the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate angels and <hi>devils.</hi> Thus you ſee, there is cauſe enough for me to reject this limitation and addition to my Major: wherefore my Argument muſt ſtand as I framed it; without this their addition: and then it is ſtrong and good to prove, that Chriſt died not for all men: and it is unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, their anſwer being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed. So far of my third Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If God the Son, died for the ſins of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105460:18"/> all men; then God the Father, will juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the perſons, and pardon the ſins of all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But God the Father, will not juſtifie the perſons, and pardon the ſins of all men:</hi> for if he ſhould, then all men ſhould be ſaved, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore God the Son, did not die for the ſins of all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for my Major, thus I prove it. 1 Arminians ſay, that by the word <hi>world,</hi> John 3.16. we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, all men in the world: now if God the Father ſo exceedingly loved all men, as to give his onely begotten Son to die for them, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. then he can do no leſs than juſtifie the perſons, and pardon the ſins of all men: becauſe, 1. He loved all men: and he gave his Son for none other end, but for all men to obtain juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and pardon of ſin: now ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God will not looſe his <hi>love,</hi> nor fail of his <hi>end,</hi> nor waſte and ſpill in vain, the <hi>bloud</hi> of his onely Son: all which he ſhould do, if he ſhould not juſtifie all men, after he had given his Son for them, and to juſtifie them. If it be in his power, will any wiſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105460:19"/> man looſe his love, be fruſtrated of his end, and ſpend all his labour and coſt in vain?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Chriſt is the <hi>Lamb</hi> of God, that <hi>taketh away</hi> the ſins of the <hi>world, John</hi> 1.29. now if Chriſt hath taken away by his death, the ſins of the <hi>world,</hi> that is, (as Arminians ſay) of all men; then God the Father, cannot <hi>retain</hi> their ſins: thoſe mens ſins, which are removed or <hi>taken away,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be unpardoned or <hi>remain</hi> upon them: wherefore if Chriſt died for all men, and hath <hi>taken away</hi> the ſins of all men, then ſurely God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath or will juſtifie and pardon the ſins of all men, or elſe, Chriſt that Lamb hath not taken away their ſins.</p>
               <p n="3">3 If God the Father, <hi>gave</hi> Chriſt his Son, to die and pacifie his wrath for the ſins of all men, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. then God the Father, cannot but <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> of his ſons death; it being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own will, and being his own <hi>gift:</hi> and if he accepts of it, then his wrath muſt needs be pacified for the ſins of all men, and ſo he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not denie to juſtifie all men, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their ſins.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105460:19"/>4 God the Father, in giving his Son; and God the Son, in giving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, both aimed at one and the ſame end, namely juſtification and pardon of ſin; and both aimed at the ſame perſons for obtaining this end: or elſe, God the Father, and God the Son, were not both of one mind, but of diverſe or contrary minds: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if God the Son died to obtain pardon of ſins for all men, then God the Father, will vouchſafe pardon of ſins to all men.</p>
               <p n="5">5 If God ſhould not juſtifie all thoſe men, for whom Chriſt died, he ſhould be unjuſt: for Chriſt gave himſelf to death, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>ranſom</hi> for all men, as Arminians ſay, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. a ranſom, is the full price for the redemption of a priſoner or captive: now when a king takes a ranſom for a thouſand captives, if he deliver not them all and every one, he is unjuſt: ſo God the Father, having taken and received at the hands of Chriſt, a full price and ranſom, for the ſins of all men, as Arminians ſay, he ſhould be unjuſt, if he ſhould not ſet free from ſin, all and every man in the world. Furthermore, if God ſhall not juſtifie
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105460:20"/> and ſet free all men, there will be fraud and folly imputed to God and Chriſt: for where there is fair and honeſt dealing, the buyer and the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler are agreed upon the ſame terms, as if the buyer intendeth to have ſo many in number, be it ten, twentie, an hundred, or a thouſand, the ſeller intendeth the ſame number alſo, and the ſame perſons: or elſe there is fraud in the one, and folly in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: now Chriſt is the <hi>purchaſer,</hi> and if he intended by his death to ranſom all men, then God the Father, muſt intend the ſame, and muſt juſtifie and deliver from wrath even all men: He muſt in juſtice deliver as many as Chriſt bought, and the ſame perſons, that is, all men in the world: or elſe, you impute fraud and folly to God and to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I ſhall inlarge my ſelf upon this laſt Argument, by deſcending to ſome particulars, as thus; If God ſhall not juſtifie and ſave eternally <hi>Judas, Pharaoh, Cain, Corah</hi> and his wicked company, for whom Chriſt died, as ſay Arminians; then he ſhall be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt: this I thus prove: If Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>Judas, Pharaoh,</hi> and other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105460:20"/> wicked men; then have they ſuffered in this life, the full wrath of God for all their ſins, and have made a ſufficient and perfect ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Gods juſtice already here: for though they ſuffered not in this life in their own perſons; yet if it be true, that Chriſt died for them, then they ſuffered in the perſon of Chriſt, when in this life he died on the Croſs for them, which is to be reckoned as their own death and ſuffering. This I thus prove; Look what a mans ſurety per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms for him, that is reckoned as done by himſelf: as, in caſe my ſurety payeth my debt, it is reckoned as my payment: for thereby I am diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. So if Chriſt paid the debt of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, Pharaoh</hi> and the reſt, it is as if they had paid it in their own perſons: and ſo they muſt be diſcharged. Hence it follows,</p>
               <p>That ſince <hi>Judas</hi> and others, have ſuffered in the perſon of Chriſt, which is to be reckoned as their own ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1. That <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> have made a full and perfect ſatisfaction to Gods juſtice for all their ſins, having ſuffered in this life the ſecond death, and hell with the pains thereof, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105460:21"/> what is equivalent thereunto. 2. That God muſt in juſtice, juſtifie and ſave this wicked crue eternally: or elſe he will be an unjuſt Judge: for he ſhall puniſh one ſin twice, once in Chriſt the ſuretie, and once again in <hi>Judas</hi> the principal. So much for proof of my Major: as for my Minor, it needs no proof, it being ſo clear.</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>Arminians do anſwer thus to my Major: That it followeth not, that if Chriſt died for all men, then God muſt juſtifie and ſave all men: for God may interpoſe the condition of <hi>faith,</hi> to go between Chriſts death for <hi>Judas</hi> and others, and the act of Gods juſtification: and ſo as though Chriſt died for all men, yet God will not juſtifie any of them, unleſs they firſt believe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>Reply.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 It is abſurd to ſuppoſe, that God would put in a <hi>condition,</hi> after he hath taken a <hi>ranſom</hi> and payment of a full price. Conditions are always made before the price is payd; but never after the price is paid and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: what man that ſelleth houſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105460:21"/> or land doth put in a condition, after he hath received his money? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſince Arminians will not have the condition of Faith, to go before Chriſts death, it is too late to put in this condition after Chriſts death: for by his death, the ranſom and price is fully paid and received; paid by Chriſt, and received by God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 If Chriſt died for <hi>Judas</hi> and all men, conſidered abſolutely as ſinners and without faith, as Arminians hold; then God the Father, muſt juſtifie <hi>Judas</hi> and all men, conſidered abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely as ſinners and without Faith, and ſo the condition of Faith cannot be interpoſed: for the Buyer and Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler (if there be fair dealings between them, ſo as one doth not over-reach the other,) are both agreed upon the ſame terms; ſo as if the Buyer pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth and payeth the price without any condition, then the Seller that takes the price, muſt give up the thing bought and paid for, without any condition: and ſo God cannot be ſaid, to put in the condition of Faith, between Chriſts death and the act of juſtification.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105460:22"/>3 Since Arminians hold, that Chriſt died for all men as ſinners, and without the condition of Faith; God cannot in juſtice require the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith, before he will juſtifie them: for if he ſhall require it, then many thouſands for whom Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dying without Faith, muſt be damned, and ſuffer for their ſins eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the next life: now if Chriſt died for them in this life, and ſuffered for them, and in their room, ſtead and place, then God ſhall be unjuſt to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh theſe men for their ſins in the next life, though they die without faith: for ſo he ſhall puniſh one ſin twice, once in Chriſt their ſuretie, and once in themſelves the principal. Since <hi>Judas</hi> hath ſuffered for his ſins, in the perſon of Chriſt in this life, God ſhall be an unjuſt Judge, to puniſh <hi>Judas</hi> for his ſins in the next life, though he hath no faith: for God hath (as they ſay) puniſhed <hi>Judas</hi> his ſins in the perſon of Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhall be unjuſt to puniſh him alſo in his own perſon. It is extream injuſtice, to require a debt both of the ſuretie, and alſo of the principal: wherefore <hi>Judas</hi> his debt, being paid
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105460:22"/> to God by Chriſt, God cannot in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice require the <hi>condition</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> of him, ſo as for want of it to damn him, and to cauſe him to ſuffer for his ſins in the next life, and ſo to pay his own debt in his own perſon: for ſo God ſhould require one debt to be twice paid: and ſo you ſee, that the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>faith,</hi> cannot be interpoſed betwixt Chriſts death, and juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; being that God in juſtice muſt juſtifie and ſet free from the debt of puniſhment, all thoſe men whoſe debt Chriſt hath paid, whether they believe or not believe: when God looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Judas,</hi> as having ſuffered in the perſon of Chriſt, he cannot but ſee his juſtice fully ſatisfied, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot but juſtifie and free him, believing or not believing: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to interpoſe the condition of Faith, is to make God an unjuſt Judge.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 I ſhall here add one thing, which will both ſtrengthen my Major, and alſo confute their anſwer. They ſay, Chriſt died for all men; and therefore they muſt ſo generally underſtand the Text, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. which ſaith, <hi>He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all,</hi> &amp;c. now all thoſe who Chriſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105460:23"/> died for, thoſe he <hi>reconciled</hi> to God his father. <hi>He is the reconciliation not for our ſins onely, but alſo for the ſins if the whole world.</hi> 1. John. 2.2. And all thoſe who Chriſt died for, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. God the Father <hi>reconciled</hi> unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>God was in Chriſt, and reconciled the world to himſelf;</hi> that is, God was in Chriſt, when he died on the Croſs for the ſins of all men, and reconciled them unto himſelf: now as God reconciled all men or the world, ſo he juſtified them all: for the Text ſaith, <hi>He did not impute their ſins unto them;</hi> 2. Cor. 5.19. Furthermore, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation,</hi> doth preſuppoſe juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to go before: for the partie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, is not ſaid to be reconciled, untill he hath firſt forgiven the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and the offender. So then the <hi>world</hi> which Chriſt died for, the ſame <hi>world</hi> God juſtified: thus you ſee my Major confirmed.</p>
                  <p>Next to confute their anſwer: Faith cannot be interpoſed betwixt Chriſts death, and Gods juſtification, ſo as to hinder any man for whom Chriſt died from juſtification: becauſe <hi>thoſe</hi> whom Chriſt died for, 1. <hi>John</hi> 2.2. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. <hi>thoſe</hi> God juſtified, <hi>not imputing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105460:23"/> their ſins unto them,</hi> 2. Cor. 5.19. and thoſe <hi>God reconciled unto himſelf,</hi> 2. Cor. 5.19. ſo Faith cannot be any condition, ſo as to hinder any man by want of it, for whom Chriſt died, from juſtification: becauſe all thoſe Chriſt died for, all thoſe God reconciled and juſtified: if Chriſt died for <hi>Judas,</hi> then God juſtified <hi>Judas;</hi> yet <hi>Judas</hi> had no faith interpoſed betwixt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petration and Application, for he was no believer. If <hi>Arminians</hi> ſay, Chriſt died for all men; then <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, God juſtified all men; and I may ſay, God juſtifieth them whether they believe or not believe: for faith cannot be interpoſed. So much for my fourth Argument.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>ARGUM. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If Chriſt died for all men, then God the Father loved all men, and that with a ſpecial and incomparable love.</hi> My reaſon here is; Becauſe God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>gave</hi> his Son, yea his onely Son to death for them: now for a Father to deliver up to death his Son, yea his onely Son, for a man; this bewrays love to that man, yea matches love. See a text for it, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105460:24"/> begotten Son,</hi> &amp;c. What greater love than this did ever God ſhew to the world, than when he <hi>gave</hi> his onely begotten <hi>Son</hi> to die for them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But God the Father did not love all men, with a ſpecial and incomparable love.</hi> This I thus prove: Becauſe there are, and ever were many unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving wicked and impenitent men in the world, who lived and died in Gods hatred: <hi>I have loved</hi> Jacob, <hi>and have hated</hi> Eſau, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13. and ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. <hi>The wicked, and him that loveth iniquitie, doth his ſoul hate,</hi> Pſal. 11.5. <hi>Thou hateſt them that work ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,</hi> Pſal. 5.5, 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore Chriſt did not die for all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To avoid the ſtrength of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, Arminians, perhaps, will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thus, That God loved all men as ſinners, but hateth them as impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hereunto I reply, That this is a diſtinction unheard of, and no where grounded in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures that I know of, and therefore it is to be rejected. That God loveth all men, as his creatures, may paſs as a ſound poſition; but that God loveth all men, as ſinners, and that with an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105460:24"/> incomparable and matchles love, is to me moſt unſound: for a thing conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as evil, is no object of love, but of hatred: and ſo much for my fifth Argument.</p>
               <p>Thus I have by five Arguments proved, That Chriſt died not for all men: and ſo I have finiſhed the firſt thing propounded at the beginning: and now I come to the ſecond, which is to make anſwer unto the Texts of Scripture, brought by Arminians to prove, That Chriſt died for all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An <hi>Anſwer</hi> unto the Texts alleadged by <hi>Arminians,</hi> to prove an <hi>Univerſal Redemption.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="section">
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>JOHN 3.16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>God ſo loved the world, that he gaue his onely begotten Son, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>BY this Text Arminians would prove, that Chriſt died for all men: and for this end, they urge the word <hi>world</hi> in the Text; which they will needs have generally and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally taken, ſo as to ſignifie all men in the world, whether good or bad, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105460:25"/> or unbelievers: and ſo as Chriſt ſhould die for all men in the largeſt ſenſe.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 I take it for a great weakneſs in Arminians, to build ſo confidently upon the word <hi>world,</hi> urging, that it muſt be generally taken here, for all men in the world: who knoweth not, that knows any thing in Scripture, that general words are very often uſed by holy pen-men particularly? The general word <hi>all,</hi> is often uſed particularly for <hi>ſome,</hi> or for <hi>many,</hi> as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.5. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. and 13.2, 7. and 9.25. and 6.12. and 10.23, 33. many examples may be given for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words alſo; but paſſing by them, I ſhall inſtance in the word in queſtion.</p>
                     <p>The word <hi>world,</hi> is ſometime taken for all men in the world, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. and ſometime it is taken for all men in the world, excepting eight perſons, as in 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20. <hi>The world that then was periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, over-flowed with water:</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it is taken for the moſt men in the world, as in 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>John</hi> 15.18, 19. and 17.9. <hi>The God of this world hath blinded the minds,</hi> &amp;c. and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it is taken for the leſſer number
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105460:25"/> of men in the world, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 17.6. <hi>John</hi> 12.19. <hi>Theſe are they which have ſubverted the ſtate of the world.</hi> And, <hi>Behold the world goeth after him.</hi> Now ſince this word is ſo variouſly uſed, how can they be ſo confident as to averr, that it muſt be taken in the largeſt ſenſe?</p>
                     <p>My anſwer therefore is, that as the word <hi>world,</hi> is ſometime taken for the leſſer number of men in the world, which are <hi>Diſciples</hi> and followers of Chriſt, as in <hi>John</hi> 12.19. ſo it may be taken alſo in their Text alleadged, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. for <hi>believers,</hi> who are the leſſer number of this world: and this is my firſt Anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 I ſhall prove, that the word <hi>world,</hi> is uſed for believers onely: and then it will follow, that as there is a world of the wicked, ſo there is a world of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers alſo: for this end,</p>
                     <p>See <hi>John</hi> 1.29. <hi>Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſins of the world.</hi> Though Arminians ſay, that Chriſt, this Lamb of God, died for the ſins of the world, and for all men, by way of <hi>Impetration;</hi> yet they hold, that Chriſt hath not juſtified, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured juſtification for all men in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105460:26"/> world, by way of <hi>Application;</hi> nor for any men but for believers onely: now this Text ſpeaks of <hi>Taking away the ſins of the world,</hi> which is no leſs, than to procure Juſtification, and to make Application of Chriſts death, by free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men from their ſins: and therefore this text is not to be underſtood, of the world of all men, but of believers onely, and of the world of believers: for no mens ſins are <hi>Taken away,</hi> but believers onely, ſee 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>God was in Chriſt, and reconciled the world unto himſelf, not imputing their ſins unto them.</hi> Here the <hi>world</hi> that were recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, &amp; juſtified, their ſins being not imputed, was not the world of all men, but of believers onely; it was the world of believers only, unles you will ſay, all men in the world are juſtified.</p>
                     <p>See <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12, 15. <hi>If the fall of them, be the riches of the world,</hi> &amp;c. Again, <hi>If the caſting away of them, be the reconciling of the world,</hi> &amp;c. Here by the <hi>world,</hi> is not meant all men in the world, but the Gentiles onely: for the Jews are not compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the word: nor are all the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles compriſed therein, but onely the believing Gentiles: for the fall of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105460:26"/> Jews, was no <hi>riches</hi> to unbelieving Gentiles; nor was the caſting away of the Jews, the <hi>reconciling</hi> of unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Gentiles: and that it is ſpoken of believing Gentiles, may further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by theſe words in the Chapter <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.11. Through their fall, <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> unto the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11, 17. Some of the <hi>branches</hi> be broken off, and thou a <hi>wild olive tree,</hi> was grafted in, and partaker of the <hi>root and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the olive tree, Rom.</hi> 11.20. Through <hi>unbelief</hi> they are broken off, and <hi>thou</hi> ſtandeſt by <hi>faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>See <hi>John</hi> 6.33. <hi>The bread of God is he which cometh down from heaven, and giveth life unto the world.</hi> Here by the word <hi>world,</hi> we muſt underſtand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and the world of believers: for Chriſt <hi>giveth</hi> not <hi>life</hi> to unbelievers.</p>
                     <p>Thus by four Texts I have proved, that the word <hi>world,</hi> is often uſed for believers, and for the world of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: now from hence my anſwer is this, that ſince the word <hi>world</hi> is often uſed for believers, &amp; for the world of believers; therefore this their allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged text <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.16. may be underſtood of believers onely, and of the world of believers: and this is my 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105460:27"/>3 I ſhall here prove, not onely (as before) that by the word <hi>world,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and the believing world may be meant; but that they are and muſt of neceſſitie be meant, and this is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the Text and context.</p>
                     <p>For this is a <hi>Rule,</hi> that general words are to be reſtrained according to the matter in hand: now the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand, or the perſons handled and ſpoken of, are believers; this you may ſee clearly expreſſed, in <hi>John</hi> 3.15, 16. That whoſoever <hi>believeth</hi> in him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> verſ. 15. God ſo loved the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that whoſoever <hi>believeth</hi> in him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> verſ. 16. wherefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, being the perſons ſpoken of, the general word <hi>world,</hi> is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to believers.</p>
                     <p>The queſtion or main thing labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be proved and cleared, is, That <hi>believers</hi> ſhall not <hi>periſh,</hi> but have <hi>life eternal,</hi> as you may ſee <hi>John</hi> 3.15. to prove and amplifie this, S. <hi>John</hi> brings a reaſon in the next verſe, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. as you may ſee by the particle (for, or becauſe.) <hi>For,</hi> God ſo loved the world, that he hath given his onely Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105460:27"/> which is as if he had ſaid, Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſhall not periſh, as the queſtion is in <hi>verſe</hi> 15. <hi>For,</hi> God ſo loved belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or the world of believers, as to give his onely ſon for them, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth, will, or ſhall hereafter believe in him, ſhall not periſh, as it is in the reaſon alleadged in <hi>verſe</hi> 16. I confeſs, the word <hi>believeth,</hi> or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Original <hi>believing,</hi> is in the preſent tenſe or time, but it muſt be underſtood of all tenſes and times, paſt, preſent, and to come: ſo as Gods love in Chriſt, was to them that did believe before Chriſts time, to them that do believe in Chriſts time, and to them that ſhall or will believe after Chriſts time: this is added, to prevent an Arminian objection, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if by <hi>world,</hi> believers be meant, then the word <hi>whoſoever,</hi> implies a diſtinction, as if there were two ſorts of believers, one believing, the other not believing at one and the ſame time: but the word <hi>whoſoever,</hi> may be underſtood diſtributively or diſtinctively, of believers before Chriſts time, of believers in Chriſts time, and of believers after Chriſts time, to the worlds end. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105460:28"/> for as much as the <hi>queſtion</hi> and thing to be amplified, was the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of believers <hi>verſe</hi> 15. it is not reaſonable, to underſtand the <hi>reaſon</hi> and amplification brought to confirm it in <hi>verſe</hi> 16. of any other perſons than believers. It were impertinent to argue thus, Believers ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; <hi>for,</hi> or becauſe God loved the world of all men, and gave Chriſt his Son for all men: this is to prove a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial and peculiar mercy belonging unto ſome men onely, by an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is general, and belongs to all men. Now by the ſame Argument, it may as ſoundly be proved, that not onely Believers ſhall not periſh, but alſo that no man in the world ſhall periſh; <hi>for,</hi> or becauſe God loved the world of all men, and gave Chriſt his Son for all men: and ſo you ſee, that by the word <hi>world,</hi> believers and the world of believers onely, muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie be meant.</p>
                     <p>The Text ſaith, <hi>God ſo loved the world:</hi> now it is clear, that God doth not love all men in the world, with ſuch a peculiar, matchleſs, &amp; <hi>incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> kind of love, as the Text ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of: for there are many thouſands
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105460:28"/> of men in the world, which God is ſo far off from loving, as that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith expreſly, God hateth them: <hi>Eſau have I hated</hi> Rom. 9.13, 22. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.5. and 6.16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.5, 6. and 11.5. wherefore, ſince God loveth not all men in the world with an incomparable love, therefore by the word <hi>world</hi> in <hi>John</hi> 3.16. can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meant, all men in the world: nor any beſides believers: for God ſo loved them onely.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 Arminians may as well ſay and hold, that all men in the world ſhall be <hi>juſtified</hi> and <hi>ſaved</hi> eternally; as to ſay and hold, that Chriſt died for all men in the world: for it is ſaid, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. God was in Chriſt, and <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled</hi> the <hi>world</hi> to himſelf, <hi>not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their ſins.</hi> If here the word <hi>world</hi> be largely taken, after the faſhion of Arminians, then all the men in the world, are <hi>reconciled</hi> to God, and their ſins <hi>forgiven,</hi> or not imputed unto them; and then they muſt be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaved. And ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15. The caſting away of the Jews, was the <hi>reconciling</hi> of the <hi>world.</hi> And ſee 1. <hi>John</hi> 2.2. He is the <hi>reconciliation</hi> for our ſins; and not for ours onely, but
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105460:29"/> alſo for the ſins of the <hi>whole world.</hi> And ſee <hi>John</hi> 1.29. Behold the Lamb of God, which <hi>taketh away</hi> the ſins of the <hi>world:</hi> ſo if by the word <hi>world,</hi> they will underſtand all men, then they muſt hold alſo, that all men in the world are reconciled to God, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, and their ſins taken away: and this is my laſt Anſwer to their Text <hi>John</hi> 3.16. and ſo I come to anſwer another of their Texts.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>1. <hi>John</hi> 2.2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he is the reconciliation for our ſins: and not for ours onely, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world.</hi> Here again they urge the word <hi>world:</hi> and ſay it muſt be taken in the largeſt ſenſe, for all men in the world: for the Text ſaith, not onely the world, as in <hi>John</hi> 3.16. but the <hi>whole world,</hi> to note the univerſalitie.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The Text ſaith, <hi>not for our ſins onely,</hi> that is, not for our ſins onely who are believers; <hi>but alſo for the ſins of the whole world,</hi> that is, for the ſins of unbelievers as well as believers: and ſo all men in the world, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and unbelievers, even the whole world are here meant.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105460:29"/>
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Enough hath been ſaid in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer anſwer, touching the word <hi>World;</hi> ſhewing that it is often taken, not for all men, but for ſome, and for many men in the world, and for the world of believers; and ſo in this laſt ſenſe it may be taken in this Text, 1. <hi>John</hi> 2.2.</p>
                     <p>But whereas they urge us in this Text, with the word <hi>whole,</hi> in that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith the <hi>whole World,</hi> this will nothing mend their cauſe: for as the word <hi>World,</hi> is often uſed for ſome, or for many men in the world, ſo are theſe words, the <hi>whole World:</hi> for this end note. 1. That other expreſſions, equivalent to this, and of as <hi>large</hi> extent as this, yet are not to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the largeſt ſenſe, but are uſed for many in the world, as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23.17. and 34.1. <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. Secondly, theſe very words in queſtion, namely the <hi>whole World,</hi> are uſed for many in the world: as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8. your faith is publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throughout the <hi>whole World:</hi> it is not credible, that every particular man and woman, in the <hi>whole World,</hi> had heard of the faith of theſe <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mans.</hi>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:105460:30"/> And ſee 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.19. we know that we are of God, and this <hi>whole World</hi> lieth in wickedneſſe. If the <hi>whole World</hi> here mentioned, ſo taken in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian</hi> ſenſe, for all and every man in the world, how could S. <hi>Iohn</hi> exempt himſelf and other godly perſons li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving then with him, from lying in <hi>wickedneſs?</hi> ſo you ſee, that by theſe words the <hi>whole World,</hi> is not always meant, all and every particular man &amp; woman in the world. <hi>Arminians</hi> may as well ſay, that S. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.19. that all men then living were wicked men, &amp; none godly; as to ſay, that the ſame Apoſtle in 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.2. ſaith, that Chriſt died for all men in the <hi>whole World,</hi> none excepted: for S. <hi>Iohn</hi> mentions the <hi>whole World,</hi> in both Texts. So much for anſwer to their firſt inference from the Text.</p>
                     <p>As for their ſecond inference from this Text, it is built upon a needleſs and groundleſs expoſition of the Text: for thus they expound it. <hi>He is the reconciliation for our ſins;</hi> that is, for the ſins of us believers now living in the world: <hi>and not for ours onely, but alſo for the ſins of the whole World;</hi> that is, not for our ſins onely who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105460:30"/> now living in the world, but alſo for the ſins of unbelievers now living in the world: and ſo he is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation for the ſins of the <hi>whole World</hi> now living, both believers and unbelievers. To this I thus anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 For them to expound the Text, as belonging to wicked ungodly men and unbelievers, muſt needs be a falſe expoſition: for it maketh God and Chriſt, to expreſs their ſingular, matchleſs, and <hi>incomparable love,</hi> unto ſuch men, as they foreſaw would live and die in their wickedneſs, hatred of God, impenitency, and unbelief: now the Scriptures inform us, that God is ſo far off from loving ſuch men, as that he <hi>hateth and abhorreth them,</hi> Pſal. 5.5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>6. Pſal. 11.5. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Text muſt not be enlarged unto unbelievers.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 The enlargement of Chriſts death and reconciliation, at the end of the verſe, may very well and ſafely be underſtood of believers onely, after this manner: He is the reconciliation not onely for our ſins, who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Iews;</hi> but alſo for the ſins of the <hi>whole world</hi> of believers, both <hi>Iews</hi> and Gentiles: or thus, He is the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105460:31"/> reconciliation not onely for our ſins, who are believers now living; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the ſins of the <hi>whole World</hi> of believers, living before our time, in our time, or that ſhall believe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. The death and reconciliation of Chriſt, is to be extended unto all times, paſt, preſent, and to come: <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, is yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever,</hi> Heb. 13.8. Thus you ſee, how this Text may well be underſtood, not of all men, but of believers onely: and this ſenſe ſuiteth well with the context, and matter in hand, or with the perſons ſpoken of, who are <hi>believers</hi> onely, as you may ſee 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1, 3. So much for anſwer to their ſecond Text, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.2. and ſo I come to their third Text.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>1. TIM. 2.6.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who gave himſelf a ranſom for all men,</hi> &amp;c. Lo, here ſay they, it is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed, that Chriſt died, and gave himſelf to death, not for ſome men onely, but for <hi>all men:</hi> and it is evident alſo by the context, that this word <hi>all,</hi> muſt be univerſally taken and in the largeſt ſenſe: for ſo it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. I exhort that prayers be made for <hi>all</hi> men, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. and for <hi>all</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:105460:31"/> that are in authority, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. who will that <hi>all</hi> men ſhall be ſaved, and come unto the acknowledging of the truth.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Here again, you ſee the weakneſs of <hi>Arminians,</hi> in that they build ſo confidently upon the word <hi>all;</hi> as if they had never read or heard, that this word <hi>all</hi> is very often uſed in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture particularly, for <hi>ſome,</hi> or for <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> as in <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.5. Then went out to him <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>all Judea,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> the region about <hi>Jordan,</hi> and were baptized, <hi>&amp;c. Matt.</hi> 4.23. Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> healed <hi>all</hi> or every ſickneſs, <hi>all</hi> or eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſeaſe, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 15.13. The God of hope fill you with <hi>all</hi> joy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but carnal joy is not prayed for here, and ſee 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. and 13.7. and 9.25. and 10.33, 23. and 6.12. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21. 3. <hi>John</hi> 12. Thus you ſee, how the word <hi>all,</hi> in 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of <hi>all</hi> that are believers; who are not <hi>all</hi> men in the world, but ſome onely, or many.</p>
                     <p>Whereas they endeavour to prove by the context, that the word <hi>all</hi> muſt be taken in the largeſt ſenſe; becauſe it is ſo taken in the former verſes: my
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105460:32"/> anſwer is, that the matter in the firſt ſix verſes is not one and the <hi>ſame,</hi> but diverſe. In <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2. the matter is about good <hi>government,</hi> but in <hi>verſ.</hi> 4, 5, 6. the matter is about mans <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> now being the matter is diverſe, therefore the word <hi>all</hi> may be diverſly underſtood, as univerſally in <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2. and particularly for <hi>ſome,</hi> in <hi>verſ.</hi> 4, 5, 6. and this is uſual in expounding of Scripture, to take the word <hi>all</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally in ſome matter treated of, and particularly in ſome other matter treated of.</p>
                     <p>Whereas they urge the fourth <hi>verſ.</hi> who will that <hi>all</hi> men ſhall be ſaved; my anſwer is, that here the word <hi>all</hi> muſt not be taken in the largeſt ſenſe: for God will not have all and every man to be ſaved: for he willeth not the ſalvation of reprobates, impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and unbelieving perſons, as you may ſee in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 13, 18, 21, 22, 27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.8, 9, 10. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 21.8. <hi>Mark.</hi> 4.11, 12.</p>
                     <p>To conclude, as the Text ſaith, He will that <hi>all</hi> men ſhall be ſaved: ſo it ſaith, that they ſhall <hi>all</hi> come to the knowledge of the truth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. now
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105460:32"/> this cannot be underſtood of all men in the largeſt ſenſe: for God doth not vouchſafe the Goſpel and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth in our time unto many <hi>Indians</hi> and wild ſavages: and before our time, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was forbidden of the holy Ghoſt, to preach the word in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Bythinia, Act.</hi> 16.6, 7. and further ſee theſe Texts <hi>Mark</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.39, 40. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.6. ſo you ſee, the word <hi>all</hi> is not univerſally to be taken: and ſo much for anſwer to their third Text.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROM. 14.15. and 1. COR. 8.11.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deſtroy not him with thy meat, for whom Chriſt died.</hi> Rom. 14.15. <hi>Through thy knowledge ſhall the weak brother pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, for whom Chriſt died.</hi> 1. Cor. 8.11. From both theſe Texts they gather, that Chriſt died for thoſe that <hi>periſh,</hi> as well as for thoſe that periſh not, but are ſaved: and if he died for thoſe that periſh, and for thoſe that periſh not; then he died for all men.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 That Chriſt died for thoſe that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh not, but are ſaved: this they ſay, we grant: and that Chriſt died alſo for thoſe that periſh, and are not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105460:33"/> this they prove by theſe two Texts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11. To this their proof I thus anſwer, To <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy</hi> is one thing, and to occation or <hi>hazard</hi> deſtruction is another. To <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> is one thing, and to occation or <hi>hazard</hi> perdition is another. Now theſe two Texts may be underſtood of the latter onely, namely of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and hazard of perdition and deſtruction: for thoſe ſtrong Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, did by their unſeaſonable uſe of meats offend the weak, and did there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by give them an occation of falling, of perdition and deſtruction: this ſenſe the contexts give light unto, both in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13. and in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9. and me think, Arminians cannot think, that the ſtrong Chriſtians, did by their unſeaſonable uſe of meats, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> and <hi>actually destroy</hi> all thoſe weak Chriſtians, who ſaw them eat theſe meats, or who by their example, were emboldened to eat them: now if they did not periſh and were indeed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, how can Arminians ſay, Chriſt died for thoſe that periſh?</p>
                     <p n="2">2 I anſwer, Whereas they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to prove, that ſome periſhed for whom Chriſt died: this is falſe, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105460:33"/> cannot be proved by theſe two Texts: for admit, that by example of the ſtrong, the weak Chriſtians did eat meats againſt their conſcience, and ſo ſinned; yet it will not follow, that they were therefore deſtroyed, and <hi>periſhed</hi> eternally: unleſs Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians will ſay, that by <hi>repentance</hi> of that ſin, they could not be ſaved; or will be ſo uncharitable, as without a ground for it, to ſay, they lived and died in this ſin without repentance. Sure I am, repentance is a ſalve for greater ſins than this, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.18. So it cannot be proved, that thoſe weak Chriſtians periſhed; and therefore it cannot be proved, that Chriſt died for thoſe that periſhed. So much for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to theſe two Texts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>HEBR. 10.29.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of how much ſoever puniſhment ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ye ſhall he be worthy, which tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth under foot the Son of God, &amp; count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the bloud of the Teſtament as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy thing, wherewith he was ſanctified.</hi> Here ſay they, are ſome men for whom Chriſt died, being that they were ſanctified by Chriſts bloud; and yet
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105460:34"/> became <hi>apoſtates,</hi> and ſhall be ſorely puniſhed: ſo then Chriſt died for thoſe that periſh, as well as for thoſe that periſh not: and if he died for both, then he died for all men.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Whereas they collect from this Text, that ſome believers and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the bloud of Chriſt, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed make apoſtaſie, and ſo as they periſhed; this collection is groundleſs: for the Text may be underſtood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally, or as a ſuppoſition; as if the Apoſtle had ſaid, <hi>If</hi> a believer, and one ſanctified by the bloud of Chriſt, ſhall make apoſtaſie and tread under foot the bloud of Chriſt, he ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or be ſurely puniſhed. Or thus, Of how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall a man be worthy, if he treads under foot the Son of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional ſpeech, or a ſuppoſition, doth not affirm and aſſert the thing to be done indeed, but onely it ſuppoſeth a thing, or puts a caſe, as in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.26, 38. ſo this Text doth not aſſert and affirm, that ſome believers either did or ſhould make apoſtaſie, and ſo periſh: that the Text may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105460:34"/> conditionally, as a ſuppoſition, and as a caſe put, I make it thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Theſe are equivalent propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; He that doth ſuch a thing, and, If one doth ſuch a thing: for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, He that ſheds mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. the which is equivalent to this, If one ſheds mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed. So in like manner, He that apoſtatizeth and treads under foot the bloud of Chriſt, ſhall periſh or be ſorely puniſhed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. the which is equivalent to this, If one apoſtatizeth and treads under foot the bloud of Chriſt, he ſhall periſh or be ſorely puniſhed, ſo it is indifferent to take either of the two expreſſions: and further note, that neither of the two do aſſert and affirm the thing to be indeed done; as it is not affirmed, that any have ſhed mans bloud, ſo it is not affirmed, that any believer hath apoſtatized, and troden under foot the bloud of Chriſt: it is onely ſaid, He that doth it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or, If one doth it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 In <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26. our tranſlators render it thus, <hi>If we ſin</hi> willingly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:105460:35"/> the which in the Original is in the participle thus, <hi>We ſinning</hi> willingly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now ſince this latter, may be rendered conditionally, (ſo it muſt be rendered, unleſs we make belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers guilty of wilfull ſinning,) why may it not be ſo too, three <hi>verſes</hi> after? for in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. in the Original it is in the participle thus, <hi>Treading</hi> under foot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which may be rendered thus, If he tread under foot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo the Apoſtle doth not aſſert or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that any man doth or hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, troden under foot the bloud of Chriſt, or made <hi>apostaſie.</hi> Note fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that in <hi>verſ.</hi> 26.27. you have the <hi>queſtion:</hi> in <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. you have the <hi>argument:</hi> and in <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. is the <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of it to the <hi>queſtion.</hi> Now where the <hi>queſtion</hi> is conditional, the application muſt not be abſolute: and therefore the 29. <hi>verſ.</hi> muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally underſtood.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 The Apoſtle ſaith in the laſt <hi>verſ.</hi> ſave one, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>If any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw</hi> himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which words, he ſpeaks of <hi>apoſtaſie</hi> and withdrawing conditionally: wherefore the <hi>apoſtaſie</hi> and treading under foot Chriſts bloud, mentioned before in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="61" facs="tcp:105460:35"/> be underſtood conditionally alſo: and ſo nothing is aſſerted as done.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 In the laſt <hi>verſ. Heb.</hi> 10.39. the Apoſtle ſpeaking of believers, as he doth alſo in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, 29. ſaith, <hi>we are not they which withdraw our ſelves.</hi> Whereby he plainly ſignifieth, that the believers of whom he wrote in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. had not, or did not <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw</hi> themſelves, or make apoſtaſie: wherefore the apoſtacy, in treading Chriſts bloud under foot, mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. is not aſſerted or affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as a thing indeed done by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers; but as a ſuppoſition, as if in caſe a believer ſhould do ſuch a thing, then he ſhould periſh or be ſorely puniſhed. So much for anſwer to this Text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>2. PET. 2.1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There ſhall be falſe teachers among you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>denying the Lord that bought them, and bring on themſelves ſwift damnation.</hi> Here ſay they, S. <hi>Peter</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, that ſome men <hi>bought</hi> by the bloud of Chriſt, ſhall be falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, bring in damnable Hereſies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Lord Chriſt, and ſhall bring on themſelves damnation: whence they argue as before, that Chriſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105460:36"/> bought or died for thoſe that periſh and <hi>are damned;</hi> and conſequently for all men: for we ſay, Chriſt died for thoſe that periſh not, but are ſaved: and they prove by this Text, that Chriſt died for thoſe that do periſh, and are damned: ſo if Chriſt died for thoſe that periſh, and for thoſe that periſh not, then he died for all men: of this ſee their <hi>Acta Synodalia de morte Chriſti,</hi> pag. 346.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p n="1">1 It cannot be proved by this Text, that Chriſt bought thoſe that <hi>did pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> and <hi>are</hi> damned: for the Text doth not expreſly ſay or intimate, that theſe falſe teachers, did ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter live and die in <hi>impenitency:</hi> for be it ſo, that they taught falſe Doctrine, brought in damnable Hereſies, and denied the Lord Chriſt Jeſus; yet they might repent of all theſe ſins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they died, and ſo be eternally ſaved: <hi>Paul</hi> when he was a <hi>Saul,</hi> was a <hi>blaſphemer,</hi> a <hi>perſecutor,</hi> and an <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor;</hi> and yet he was upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Pentance received to mercy, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13, 16. and he thought he was bound to do, <hi>many contrary things againſt the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105460:36"/> name of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Act. 26.9, 10, 11. whereby he denied the Lord that bought him, and yet he was not damned.</p>
                     <p>But perhaps they will urge the laſt words of the Text, that <hi>they ſhall bring on themſelves ſwift damnation.</hi> To which I anſwer, that from theſe words it cannot be proved, that they <hi>were</hi> damned: for theſe words muſt be underſtood with an exception, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they repent: as <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10. every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit, <hi>is hewn down, and caſt into the fire,</hi> that is, unleſs they repent. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 21.8. But the fearfull, and the unbelieving, <hi>&amp;c. ſhall have their part in the lake, which burneth with fire and brimſtone,</hi> that is, if they repent not, but go on ſtill in their ſins till death: ſo, they ſhall bring on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſwift damnation, unleſs they repent, and this is my firſt anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Whereas <hi>Arminians</hi> underſtand by the word [Lord] in the Text, the Lord Chriſt Jeſus: and by the word [bought] in the Text, the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from ſin and eternal wrath by the bloud of Chriſt: I deny both theſe ſenſes of the words; and ſhall ſhew,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105460:37"/> that they may be well and ſafely ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in other ſenſes, which will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing further their cauſe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, for the word <hi>Lord:</hi> it may be underſtood of God the Father, or of God in general: for the clearing up of this, note, that in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the word whereby Chriſt is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted uſually is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> tranſlated Lord; but in this Text of <hi>Peter,</hi> we have an other word, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and tranſlated Lord: and being an <hi>other word,</hi> and not uſual to note Chriſt, it is likely enough to be of an <hi>other ſenſe:</hi> we find this word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> tranſlated Lord, and uſually applied to God the Father, or to God in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, or to earthly and fleſhly Lords and Maſters, not unto Chriſt as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, as in theſe Texts, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.29. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.24. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Jude</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.1, 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. wherefore ſince this word is uſually, ſpeaking of God, underſtood of God the Father, why may it not be ſo underſtood alſo in this their Text, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. and ſince it is ſeldom, or rather never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Chriſt as Redeemer, why ſhould it be ſo underſtood in this Text, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</p>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:105460:37"/>
                     <p>Secondly, for the word <hi>bought:</hi> this may be underſtood of Gods buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and redeeming his people, from their bondage in Egypt, or from ſome other ſlavery, ſervitude, and bondage to their enemies; of which you may read in <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.26. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.23. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.7.2, 3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.21. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.10, 11. And then the words of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> may be underſtood as an agravation of the ſin of thoſe falſe teachers, for that they ſhould bring into the Church, ſuch damnable He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, as whereby they ſhould deny even the <hi>Lord their God,</hi> who bought and redeemed them from ſervitude and ſlavery, unto their oppreſſing enemies in the fleſh. And the rather this ſenſe may ſtand, becauſe it ſo well ſuites with the other word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Lord,</hi> the which is taken for God the Father, but ſeldom or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther never for Chriſt the Redeemer, and this is my ſecond anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="3">3 As touching the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, tranſlated <hi>bought</hi> them: it may be rendered <hi>taught</hi> them: it may be tranſlated <hi>taught:</hi> ſee <hi>Criſpine</hi> and <hi>Scapula,</hi> who ſay, that the Noun <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, hath (beſides an other ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation)
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105460:38"/> this for one, it ſignifieth an <hi>oration</hi> or <hi>ſermon:</hi> &amp; the Verbs <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſignifie to <hi>preach</hi> or <hi>teach:</hi> yea the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſignifies not onely to <hi>buy,</hi> but alſo to <hi>conſult,</hi> and to <hi>give counſel:</hi> wherefore the Text may be thus tranſlated: <hi>Deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord that taught them,</hi> or <hi>gave them counſel.</hi> Now this makes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for proof that the Lord bought them, or redeemed them: and this is my third Anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 If for all this, they will preſs the Text, and underſtand it of the Lord Chriſt, and that he hath bought and <hi>redeemed</hi> wicked perſons and unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. they may as well ſay alſo, that God <hi>juſtified</hi> the world of wicked men and unbelievers, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. and that God <hi>juſtifieth</hi> the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as ungodly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. which is contrary to <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15. and ſo much for anſwer to this their Text, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ROM. 5.6.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For when we were yet without ſtrength, in due time Chriſt died for the ungodly.</hi> Lo here ſay they, is it not ſaid expreſly, that Chriſt died for the ungodly? If therefore Chriſt died as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105460:38"/> well for the ungodly, as for the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then Chriſt died for all men, for good and bad.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>There is another Text of like kind, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Chriſt hath once ſuffered, the Just for the unjuſt,</hi> &amp;c. Wherefore one Anſwer ſhall ſerve to both.</p>
                     <p>True it is, that Chriſt died for the ungodly, and for the unjuſt: and had he not died for ſuch, it had been wo to all godly perſons: for as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the godly and believing Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that there was a time, when they were ungodly and unjuſt, as <hi>idolaters, adulterers, drunkards,</hi> and <hi>extortioners,</hi> &amp;c. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. ſo may I ſay, there was a time before our converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when we were ungodly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt: if therefore Chriſt had not died for ungodly and unjuſt perſons, no godly man now living could poſſibly be ſaved.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore we muſt diſtinguiſh of ungodly perſons thus: There are ſome ungodly perſons, who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come believing and penitent godly perſons: and for theſe ungodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Chriſt died, as the Text ſaith:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105460:39"/> and of ſuch the Text ſpeaketh, as is plain <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6, 8, 10. but there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ungodly perſons, who perſiſt ſtill even unto death in their ungodlineſs, refuſing to repent and believe: now I denie that Chriſt died for theſe; or that the Text is to be underſtood of theſe. Theſe are <hi>dogs</hi> and <hi>ſwine,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>pearl</hi> is not to be given to theſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6. Chriſt would not vouchſafe to <hi>pray</hi> for theſe, <hi>John</hi> 17.9. and therefore he would not <hi>die</hi> for them: and this is my Anſwer to this Text.</p>
                     <p>Thus I have made anſwer, to all the Texts of Scripture, which ſeem to have any weight in them, for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian cauſe: they have alſo ſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, as two or three, but the one of them onely deſerves an anſwer, ſo paſſing by the other, I ſhall here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it, and make anſwer to it: you ſhall find it in their <hi>Acta Synodalia</hi> pag. 337. <hi>de Morte Chriſti</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>ARGUMENT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoſoever are bound to believe in Chriſt Jeſus, for them Chriſt died.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But all men are bound to believe in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:105460:39"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore for all men Chriſt died.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the Major they prove it by this reaſon: becauſe if it be not true, ſome men, as thoſe for whom Chriſt died not, are bound to believe a <hi>lye</hi> or a <hi>falſhood:</hi> which is very abſurd. The Minor they prove by this Text, <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 36.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>I denie their Major: for it is not true, that Chriſt died for all thoſe men who are bound to believe in him: that is, to believe in him, that he is the Son of God, and Saviour of the world, which is the right object of faith. And as for the reaſon, whereby they labour to prove their Major, it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound: for it leans upon an unſound (though common) deſcription of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith: for they deſcribe it thus: <hi>Faith in Chriſt, is a certain &amp; full or plerophorie perſwation of the mind, whereby we embrace Chriſt, with this confidence, that he died not onely for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but alſo for us, or for me and my ſins in particular.</hi> This deſcription however common, yet is it unſound: for it cannot be proved in Scripture: for I no where find in the Scripture,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105460:40"/> that the object of faith, is to believe that Chriſt died for <hi>us,</hi> or for <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>me</hi> in particular, as they ſuppoſe in their Argument: this I deny, and they muſt prove it if they can, and when they can. The object of juſtifying and ſaving faith is, to believe that <hi>Chriſt is the Son of God,</hi> the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the world, and the like: and this is the current of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures every where: in particular ſee <hi>John</hi> 20.31. <hi>Theſe things are written, that ye might believe, that Jeſus is that Chriſt the Son of God: and that in or ſo believing, ye might have life,</hi> &amp;c. All men may be bound to believe this, and yet not bound to believe a <hi>lye:</hi> or thoſe for whom Chriſt died not, may be bound to believe all this, and yet not be bound to believe a <hi>lye</hi> or a <hi>falſhood.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now that the Scriptures do every where make this the object of faith, that <hi>Chriſt is the Son of God,</hi> the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias,</hi> the <hi>Saviour</hi> of the world, and the like; beſide the Text alleadged <hi>John</hi> 20.31. See alſo theſe Texts, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.16. the object of S. <hi>Peters</hi> faith, whereof he made confeſſion unto, and before Chriſt, was this, <hi>Thou art Chriſt,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105460:40"/> the Son of the living God.</hi> Acts 8.37. The object of the <hi>Eunuch's</hi> faith was the ſame, <hi>I believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God.</hi> Acts 9.20. the ſum of <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching, to beget ſaving faith in men, was this, That <hi>Chriſt was that Son of God.</hi> Acts 2.36. the ſum of <hi>Peters</hi> ſermon, as touching Faith, whereby he converted three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſouls unto the faith, was this, That he whom they had crucified, <hi>God had made him both Lord and Chriſt.</hi> 1. <hi>John</hi> 5.5. who is he that overcometh the world, but he who believeth, that <hi>Jeſus is that Son of God?</hi> So you ſee, the <hi>victorious faith</hi> is, to believe, that Chriſt is the Son of God. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.3, 4. <hi>Paul</hi> preached, that Chriſt died and roſe again; and that <hi>this is Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And by this ſermon of Chriſt, he won many to the faith, as you may ſee in the fourth verſe. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.5. here you have another ſermon of <hi>Pauls,</hi> that <hi>Jeſus was the Chriſt;</hi> and this is the object of faith. <hi>John</hi> 1.29, 34. S. <hi>Johns</hi> ſermon was this, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſins of the world,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>This is that Son of God.</hi> John 1.49, 50. <hi>Nathanaels</hi> confeſſion of faith, was this, <hi>Thou art that Son of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105460:41"/> God.</hi> John 4.7, 25, 29, 39, 42. The faith of the <hi>woman</hi> of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Samaritanes, was this, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and <hi>the Chriſt:</hi> and that <hi>Jeſus was that Chriſt, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world.</hi> John 11.27. the faith of <hi>Martha</hi> was, that <hi>Chriſt was the Son of God.</hi> Thus you ſee, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the current of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the object of faith is, To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Chriſt is the Son of God, the Saviour, with the like: now all men may be bound to believe theſe things of Chriſt, and yet not be bound to believe a <hi>lye,</hi> or thoſe for whom Chriſt died not, may be bound to believe theſe things of Chriſt, and yet are not bound to believe a <hi>falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood:</hi> nor hence will it follow, that Chriſt died for them that are bound to believe this. But I no where read, that Chriſt required, or that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preached for ſuch a particular applicatorie faith as this, That Chriſt is <hi>mine,</hi> or that Chriſt died for <hi>our</hi> ſins, or that Chriſt died for <hi>thee,</hi> or for <hi>me</hi> in particular.</p>
                     <p>I confeſs I read of <hi>Thomas</hi> his faith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.28. ſaying, <hi>Thou art my Lord and my God.</hi> And of <hi>Pauls</hi> faith, <hi>Gal.</hi>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:105460:41"/> 2.20. ſaying, <hi>Who hath loved me, and given himſelf for me.</hi> Theſe indeed were acts of the two <hi>Apoſtles</hi> faith; but I no where read, that Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of <hi>every man</hi> this faith, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſalvation; nor do I read, that the Apoſtles or any one of them, did <hi>preach</hi> this faith to the people, when in their ſermons they preached to beget men unto the faith: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I judge, 1. That this kind of faith is proper unto Apoſtles, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtians of the higheſt form in the ſchool of Chriſt; and not common to every weak Chriſtian: for how then ſhould they be ſaved? ſince many hundreds of <hi>weak Chriſtians,</hi> neither can nor dare ſay, Chriſt is <hi>mine:</hi> or Chriſt died for <hi>me</hi> in particular. 2. I judge, that this act or kind of faith, is a conſequent of juſtifying faith, and may ſafely and comfortably be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and collected, by ſtrong Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from it, thus; He that hath juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith, Chriſt is <hi>his,</hi> and Chriſt died for <hi>him.</hi> But I in particular have juſtifying faith: for I believe, that Chriſt is the Son of God, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world; and my faith is accompanied with good works, as
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105460:42"/> Sanctification and Mortification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore Chriſt is <hi>mine,</hi> and Chriſt died for <hi>me</hi> in particular. So much for clearing of my Anſwer: and ſo much alſo for anſwer to their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>By this time we have finiſhed theſe things propounded to be handled; Firſt we have by ſundrie Arguments proved, That Chriſt died not for all men. Secondly, we have anſwered all their Texts of Scripture, and their Argument, whereby they would prove the contrary. Now in the third place, we confute a common anſwer of Arminians, which they give to a notable objection of ours.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:105460:42"/>
               <head>The Confutation of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Anſwer of <hi>Arminians,</hi> which they give to a notable Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ours.</head>
               <p>FIrſt I ſhall propound <hi>our</hi> Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Secondly I ſhall give you the <hi>Arminian</hi> anſwer. And Thirdly I ſhall confute it in my Reply.</p>
               <div type="objection">
                  <head>Objection.</head>
                  <p>If Chriſt died for <hi>Judas,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wicked and ungodly men, why are they not all <hi>ſaved?</hi> how can any be <hi>damned,</hi> for whom Chriſt died? for if Chriſt died for them, then have they ſuffered in this life in the perſon of Chriſt their ſuretie, the torments of the next life, which Chriſt upon the Croſs bore for them, and in their room and place: now God having pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed <hi>Judas</hi> and the reſt, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt on the Croſs in this life, with the puniſhment due to the next life; he cannot puniſh them again in the next life, unleſs he be an unjuſt Judge, puniſhing the ſame men for the ſame ſins twice: once in this life, and once more in the next life: and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105460:43"/> therefore <hi>Iudas</hi> and all other men, muſt be ſaved, if Chriſt died for all men.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>Hereunto <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians both, make this anſwer, <hi>Iudas</hi> and the reſt will not <hi>believe:</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to believe in Chriſt, and ſo to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply him: and therefore God may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly damn them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. ſee their <hi>Acta Synodalia, de Morte Chriſti,</hi> pag. 320. and this they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to clear by ſome ſimilitudes: If a <hi>Phyſician</hi> tenders a potion to a patient, he is not to be blamed, if the patient will not receive it and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it; but the fault and blame is onely in the patient. So if God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Chriſt, to <hi>Iudas</hi> and all other wicked men; but they will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him and apply him, then the blame is theirs, and ſo God is free of injuſtice, though he damn them. An other ſimily is this; A <hi>King</hi> having many ſubjects in captivity under a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign King, payes a full and ſufficient ranſom for every one of them; now many of thoſe captives deſpiſe their liberty, and chuſe to live in captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and bondage; In this caſe there is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:105460:43"/> no blame in the King, but in the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives onely: So God and Chriſt have ranſomed all men, but many men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe this ranſom, by refuſing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and ſo chooſe to live in captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and thraldom ſtill; wherefore if God keep them under everlaſting thraldom, he is not unjuſt or blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but theſe deſpiſers onely are blameable.</p>
                     <div type="reply">
                        <head>Reply.</head>
                        <p>I ſhall firſt deal with their anſwer, and then with their ſimilitudes: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with their anſwer.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 Be it ſo, that <hi>Judas</hi> doth not and will not believe, but obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſeth to believe; yet this freeth not God of injuſtice if he damn <hi>Judas;</hi> ſuppoſing that Chriſt died for <hi>Judas:</hi> for clearing of this, I aſk <hi>Arminians,</hi> whether Chriſt died for men, conſidered as believers, or as ſinners and unbelievers? Hereunto they will not ſay, as believers: for ſo they ſhould juſtifie our Doctrine, which is, that Chriſt died for belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and for them onely: wherefore they muſt anſwer, that Chriſt died for men conſidered as ſinners and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out belief; and ſo faith is no conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105460:44"/> of <hi>impetration,</hi> or of Chriſts death and ranſom paid for men: now if Chriſt impetrating, and paying a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for men, did it abſolutely and without any condition or conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith in them; then for <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> God the Father cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>faith</hi> in men before application, or before he will apply Chriſt his death unto them in juſtification: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they will abſurdly think, that Chriſt and God were not of one and the ſame mind, but were at <hi>odds</hi> and difference in the work of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as if Chriſt ſhould buy and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe us abſolutely without a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but God ſhould ſell us upon a condition; ſo abſurdly they ſhould think, the <hi>buyer</hi> and <hi>ſeller</hi> ſhould be at odds, and not agreed both upon the ſame terms: now ſince it muſt follow, that if Chriſt died for <hi>Iudas</hi> without reſpect to faith in him, then God cannot but juſtifie and ſave <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> without regard to faith in him; then though <hi>Judas</hi> doth not believe, and wilfully refuſeth to believe, yet God cannot in juſtice damn him for his not believing: becauſe when Chriſt <hi>bought Iudas</hi> of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:105460:44"/> and God the Father <hi>ſold Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> to Chriſt, there was no conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith intended betwixt them: and therefore <hi>Iudas</hi> muſt be ſaved. If you ſay, that Chriſt died for <hi>Iudas,</hi> then God cannot require <hi>faith</hi> of him, ſo as he ſhould for his infidelity, in juſtice damn &amp; puniſh him in the next life; God cannot be ſo unjuſt, as to puniſh one man twice for his ſins, as once in Chriſt his ſurety, and once again in himſelf the principal; one debt muſt not be twice payed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to alleadge a reaſon from <hi>Iudas</hi> his <hi>unbelief,</hi> why God may damn him in the next life, is to alleadge a reaſon, why God may deal unjuſtly in the next life.</p>
                        <p>Now what they ſhould ſay to this I cannot deviſe, unleſs they will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh of <hi>Iudas</hi> his ſins, and ſo make an hotchpotch of the work of <hi>Redemption,</hi> ſaying, that Chriſt died for ſome of <hi>Iudas</hi> his ſins, but not for all, as not for his unbelief: and then it will follow, that Chriſt is made an <hi>half</hi> Saviour, or a partial Saviour: and Chriſt died for ſome of <hi>Iudas</hi> his ſins, and <hi>Iudas</hi> dieth for other ſome of his ſins: and, Chriſt died for all <hi>Iudas</hi> his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:105460:45"/> ſins ſave that one of unbelief, and <hi>Iudas</hi> is now in Hell for no ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but ſuffers onely for one ſin, namely his unbelief: theſe are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and groundleſs fantaſies, never broched by any Chriſtian man, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Arminians</hi> will be the firſt. 2. So ſaying, they contradict themſelves: For if Chriſt died not for unbelief, then he died not for all men: for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men are unbelievers, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. Chriſts death was for believers, or for unbelievers: we ſay, it was for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, <hi>ergo</hi> they muſt hold, that it was for unbelievers. So much touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their anſwer; and now I come to their ſimilitudes, and firſt to that of a Phyſician.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 This ſimily of a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together impertinent to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for by this ſimily it is cleared, that God in juſtice may damn <hi>Judas</hi> once, becauſe he refuſeth to believe; but it doth not clear that which is in queſtion, which is, that God in juſtice may damn <hi>Judas twice</hi> for his ſin of unbelief; that is, once in his ſurety Chriſt, and once more in his own perſon: this is high injuſtice: no ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes may or can make God to be unjuſt.</p>
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:105460:45"/>
                        <p>If the patient refuſeth to receive and apply the potion, he is to bear the blame; but it is not ſo in <hi>Judas,</hi> if he refuſeth to believe and apply Chriſt: becauſe if Chriſt died for <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> abſolutely, and without reſpect to his belief or unbelief, as Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians ſay, then he is not bound to believe in Chriſt, as a <hi>means</hi> to free him from damnation; for Chriſt hath already ſuffered his damnation for him, before God the Father required any faith in him, when he died for him, conſidered as a ſinner or unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever: ſo <hi>Judas</hi> is not to be blamed for not believing; ſince Chriſt in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him and in his room, required or reſpected no faith in him; and it is too late for God the Father, to require the condition of faith in him, after he hath puniſhed him and his ſin in Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>Further, though in Phyſick, the patient is to apply the potion to avoid death, yet it is not ſo in the potion of Chriſts death, to free us from death: for here <hi>man</hi> is to do nothing, but to be <hi>paſſive,</hi> if Chriſt died for all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers; but it is <hi>God</hi> who is to make application, &amp; to apply Chriſts
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105460:46"/> death to men, whether they believe or believe not: becauſe he received and <hi>accepted</hi> Chriſts death for all men, believers or not believers: in what condition Chriſt <hi>gave</hi> himſelf for men, in ſuch condition God <hi>received</hi> Chriſt for men.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 Though a Phyſician tenders a potion to his patient, ſo as he refuſeth to apply it he muſt die; yet it is not ſo to be applied, as if God tendered Chriſt upon the condition of faith, ſo as if they refuſe to believe they muſt be damned: for it is abſurd to think or ſay, that after God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and <hi>accepted</hi> of Chriſt and his death for men, without any conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all, be it faith or any other; he ſhould afterwards require a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or tender Chriſt upon a condition of faith. God having received Chriſts death for men without condition, he hath no tender to make unto men now, but to tender them juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, glorification, and freedom from condemnation; this or nothing is to be tendered: for after God hath pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and damned a man in Chriſt, it is moſt abſurd to think, he ſhould then require of him, faith as a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:105460:46"/> and <hi>means</hi> to free him from damnation. Thus much for the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of a <hi>Phyſicia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="2">2 As for the other ſimile of a <hi>King</hi> and the Captives, this is alſo imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: for 1. Be it ſo, that <hi>Judas</hi> and other captives do deſpiſe Chriſts ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and faith the means of it, yet this will not clear God of injuſtice, if he puniſh <hi>Judas twice;</hi> once in Chriſt his ſuretie, and once again in his own perſon: no ſimile can make God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, or to puniſh one man or one ſin twice: God in juſtice may puniſh <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> his diſpiſing once, as in Chriſt, or in <hi>Judas;</hi> but not twice, as in Chriſt and in <hi>Judas</hi> both. 2. This ſimile is unfit for the purpoſe, and therefore to be rejected: if it were fitted to our queſtion, it ſhould be thus framed: A <hi>King</hi> having many ſubjects in captivity to a forreign King, pays their ranſom by his ſon, who is put into captivitie for them, and lies there in their room; but they deſpiſe their libertie, chooſe to live in captivitie ſtill; wherefore the forreign King, may keep both the Kings <hi>ſon,</hi> and the <hi>captives</hi> alſo in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and captivitie: can the forreign King do this injuſtice? So much
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:105460:47"/> for their ſecond ſimilitude.</p>
                        <p>I cannot imagine what Arminians ſhould ſay to evade theſe things, unleſs they will coyn a new diſtinction, and ſtrange to Chriſtian ears, and ſo make a hotchpotch of the work of <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſaying, that Chriſt died for ſome of a mans ſins, but not for all his ſins, as not for his final unbelief, or <hi>new infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie,</hi> or infidelitie unrepented of, as they expreſs it: and then they think to evade all by this anſwer, that God puniſhed Chriſt for all <hi>Judas</hi> his ſins, excepting his infidelitie, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed <hi>Judas</hi> for his infidelitie; and ſo God puniſheth no ſin twice, nor is he unjuſt. But to this new diſtinction I thus reply.</p>
                        <p n="1">1 It maketh Chriſt to be but a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Saviour, or an <hi>half</hi> Saviour: for by this diſtinction they ſay, Chriſt died for ſome, or many of a mans ſins, but not for all; for not for unbelief. 2. It maketh Chriſt to die for ſome of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> his ſins, and <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf to die for other ſome of his ſins. 3. It ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>Judas</hi> and other wicked men and unbelievers, to ſuffer hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for none of all their horrible and abominable ſins committed in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:105460:47"/> their life time; but onely for their fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal unbelief: for they ſay, Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuffered for all their other ſins. Now to ſay that wicked men do not ſuffer in hell, for their other horrible ſins beſides infidelitie, is not onely abſurd, but manifeſtly falſe: as is to be ſeen <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41, 42, 43. <hi>John</hi> 5.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6, 8, 9. <hi>Jude</hi> 7. <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8. where we ſee, that wicked men ſuffer in hell, for their <hi>unmercifulneſs, contention, unrighteouſneſs, fornication, murther, ſorcerie, idolatrie, and lyes:</hi> ſo you ſee, they can make no evaſion, but by coyning of a new diſtinction, which makes an hotchpotch of the work of Redemption, and is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abſurd, but alſo manifeſtly falſe, as is proved. 2. If Chriſt died not for new infidelitie, then he died not for all men: for many believe not after invitation by the Goſpel preached, which they call, new infidelitie, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.37. So much for confutation of the Arminian anſwer, ſaying to us, that <hi>therefore God may juſtly damn</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, <hi>becauſe he will not believe.</hi> Now their <hi>anſwer</hi> being confuted, our <hi>obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> remains good, namely, that if Chriſt died for all men, then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:105460:48"/> that no man ſhall be damned, but that <hi>Judas</hi> and all men ſhall be ſaved. And ſo I come to the fourth and laſt thing propounded to be handled, which is, A Confutation of their diſtinction of <hi>Impetration</hi> and <hi>Application.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The diſtinction of <hi>Impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Application</hi> confuted.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt we muſt know what Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans underſtand by theſe terms. By <hi>impetration,</hi> they underſtand the death and paſſion of Chriſt, whereby he me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited remiſſion of ſins and juſtification for all men. By <hi>application,</hi> they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the fruit and benefit of Chriſts death and paſſion; which is (as I conceive it muſt be) the real and actual remiſſion of ſins and juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, applied unto the faithfull. The former, namely Impetration, is proper to God the Son: the latter, namely Application, is proper unto God the Father. Furthermore, they place Faith, between Impetration and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:105460:48"/> ſo as though Chriſt died and impetrated for all men, yet God juſtifies, and makes application of Chriſts death unto believers onely: now the better to help on the matter, they ſay, that theſe being acts of <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>favour,</hi> God may according to his infinite <hi>wiſdom,</hi> order them according to his moſt free will: the which words, as I take it, are ſpoken in relation to Faith, that God may place it before or after impetration, as it pleaſeth his wiſdom. Having thus opened their meaning, I thus proceed.</p>
                  <p>As for this diſtinction of Impetrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Application, I acknowledge it: for as it is Chriſt that died or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated for us, ſo it is God that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth us, and makes application of Chriſts death unto us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. And I am content, that they call what Chriſt did for us on the Croſs, Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration; and what God doth for us in relation to it, and by virtue of it, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: but I miſlike of their <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> that they ſhould divide the works of Chriſt and God; ſo as if Chriſt ſhould impetrate and die for many men, to whom God makes no appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Chriſts death: for they ſay,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:105460:49"/> Chriſt impetrated for all men, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and unbelievers, but God applies Chriſts death for juſtification to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers onely: now thus the Works of Chriſt and God, do not concurr in the ſame perſons, but are divided: for God makes no application unto many men, for whom Chriſt made impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. On the contrary we hold, that the works of God the Father, and God the Son, are undivided: diſtinguiſhed they may be, but divided they may not be: they always concurr as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame perſons; to whomſoever God makes application, to and for thoſe and none other Chriſt made im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrations; and for whomſoever Chriſt impetrated, to thoſe and to all thoſe God makes application. And as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>faith,</hi> we hold, that as God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth faith in application, ſo Chriſt reſpecteth faith in impetration, ſo as faith is precedent in both: and ſo God and Chriſt, had reſpect unto the ſame perſons, and unto the ſame qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the perſons: but that faith is to come between impetration and application, is but an Arminian deviſe; dividing the conſideration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:105460:49"/> and the <hi>Son,</hi> about one and the ſame work of Redemption: and ſo I come to the Confutation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 For the abſurdnes of this diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of impetration and application; &amp; the Arminian deviſe, of faith coming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, as a condition of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter onely: put caſe, that a King, having ſubjects in thraldom and captivity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a forreign King, and to ranſom &amp; redeem them, he ſends his onely Son, to lay in bondage and captivity for them and in their ſtead and place; and this the King doth without any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all, to be performed by his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: If now the forreign King, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to deliver &amp; ſet free the ſubjects, unleſs they will perform ſome condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion firſt, which he impoſeth upon them, and which their own King never required of them in ſending his Son, nor did his Son go into captivity for them upon any ſuch condition: is it not abſurd to imagine, that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign King ſhould require a condition to be performed by the ſubjects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will apply the ranſom to them, and ſet them free? it muſt needs be abſurd, for you muſt imagine, folly &amp; ignorance in the one King, or fraud
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:105460:50"/> and deceit in the other <hi>King,</hi> in that they were not firſt agreed both on the ſame terms, before the ſon was put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captivity. So is the caſe, if Faith goeth between impetration and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and if Chriſt died for men ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely without the condition of Faith, and yet God will require the condition of Faith, before he will make application &amp; ſet men free from their ſins and condemnation.</p>
                  <p>I know nothing they have to ſay, to free themſelves of this abſurdity but this, that both the Kings, Chriſt and God, were at the firſt agreed on the ſame terms, as thus: they both agreed, that Chriſt ſhould impetrate and die for all men abſolutely, without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of any faith in them; but that God ſhould apply Chriſts death to none but believers, or to ſuch as did firſt believe: To this I reply, that this occaſion is guilty of theſe abſurdities.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That the King ſhould put his one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſon, to live in thraldom and bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; and his ſon ſhould willingly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all this miſery, for millions, even the greater number of his ſubjects in captivity, whom he <hi>foreſaw</hi> and knew well, ſhould not be a ruſh the better
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:105460:50"/> for it, becauſe they would not keep the condition agreed on. Will any wiſe man, give and pay a certain price cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, for an uncertain poſſeſſion, be it of houſe or land? much leſs will any pay aforehand, for that land or houſe, which he foreſees he ſhall never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy? yet ſuch a purchaſer they make Chriſt to be by this agreement.</p>
                  <p>The abſurdneſs alſo of this may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by this ſimile: <hi>Abraham</hi> bought of the <hi>Hittites,</hi> for 400 ſhekels of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, a field to bury his wife in; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the payment of the mony, the field was delivered to him for a poſſeſſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now is it not abſurd to imagine, that <hi>Abraham</hi> and the <hi>Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites,</hi> ſhould both be agreed, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> ſhould buy and pay for the field abſolutely without any conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but yet the <hi>Hittites</hi> ſhould require a condition to go between paying and poſſeſſion, and before <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould have poſſeſſion? and without it, no poſſeſſion? where a condition is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, it always goes before pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; never after, or between pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and poſſeſſion: ſo though they in words aſcribe <hi>wiſdom</hi> to God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that God may according to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:105460:51"/> wiſdom, order Faith to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after impetration, yet in this caſe indeed, they impute abſurdneſs and <hi>folly</hi> to God, in puting the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith after the price of Chriſts death. (The caſe is the ſame, in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or for a mans friend or friends, as Chriſt did.)</p>
                  <p n="1">1 They ſay, Chriſts <hi>intention</hi> was by his death to <hi>ſave</hi> all men, even unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in <hi>Acta Synodalia,</hi> pag. 344. now for Chriſt to agree with God, to put in a condition of <hi>Faith</hi> after im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petration, is a contradiction and croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his <hi>intenſion:</hi> for by his death, he intended to ſave unbelievers, but by agreeing to require Faith of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, or they to be denied ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he (foreſeing they would not and ſhould not believe) <hi>intended</hi> not to have them ſaved: for he agreed to a condition which barred them from ſalvation: ſo much for the abſurdity of this agreement.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 An other abſurdity in the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is this: It maketh God to be an <hi>unjuſt Judge:</hi> for Chriſt by his impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration and dying for the ſins of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, hath born the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:105460:51"/> their ſins for them in this life; now for God to puniſh unbelievers for their ſins in the next life (as he will <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16.) is to puniſh twice o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for the ſame ſins, which is an act of injuſtice in God: now this muſt be ſo, if you diſtinguiſh of impetration and application in ſuch ſort, as they concurr not in the ſame perſons, but are divided, ſo as impetration belongs unto unbelievers, but application be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to them: for if application and juſtification belongs not to them, then they muſt ſuffer puniſhment for their ſins in the next life, and ſo God ſhall be unjuſt: for after he hath pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unbelievers in Chriſt their <hi>ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> he ſhall puniſh them again, in their own perſons: ſo you ſee, impetration and application are not to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in reſpect of perſons, as if the one belonged to ſome perſons, but not the other, unleſs you will make God to be an unjuſt Judge.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 I ſhall confute this diſtinction by a Text of Scripture, underſtanding it in the Arminian ſence: ſee 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15, 19. In <hi>verſe</hi> 15. ſpeaking of Chriſt and his death, it ſaith, <hi>one died for all,</hi> &amp;c. Here I underſtand the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:105460:52"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:105460:52"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:105460:53"/> word <hi>all,</hi> in the Arminian ſenſe: and then in <hi>verſe</hi> 19. it ſpeaketh again of Chriſt and his death, ſaying, <hi>God was in Chriſt,</hi> (that is, in Chriſt upon the Croſs, when he died for all) <hi>and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled the world unto himſelf, not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their ſins unto them.</hi> So here you have the impetration of Chriſts death; and the application of it, in reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and not imputation of ſins: now here <hi>application,</hi> is made as large as <hi>impetration,</hi> and to belong unto the ſame perſons, without diſtinction or diviſion: for thoſe [all] which Chriſt died for, were all of them reconciled to God, and juſtified, <hi>their ſins not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imputed unto them:</hi> the ſame <hi>world</hi> which Chriſt died for, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. the ſame was reconciled and had no ſins imputed to them. So S. <hi>Paul</hi> did not allow of this Arminian diſtinction and diviſion, of impetration and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the Arminian ſenſe, ſo as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petration ſhould be underſtood more largely for perſons than application; or as if impetration had been for all men, and application but for ſome men.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 This diſtinction is guiltie yet of another abſurditie, for it makes the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:105460:53"/> 
                     <hi>means</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> to be uſed altogether too late, and ſo to become an unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and frivolous means: for Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians make faith to be a means to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void an evil, after the evil is paſt. They ſay, Chriſt by his <hi>impetration,</hi> ſuffered the evil of death for unbelievers: now in as much as Chriſt ſuffered death, and bore the evil of puniſhment of unbelievers, for them and in their ſtead and room, they themſelves have ſuffered death, and bore the evil of puniſhment in the perſon of Chriſt: now after unbelievers have born the evil of puniſhment, it is too late to uſe <hi>faith</hi> as a means to obtain <hi>appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and juſtification, and a freedom from the evil of puniſhment: for thus they ſhould uſe a means to avoid an evil, after the evil is paſt, and ſo the means of faith is made unprofitable and frivolous: wherefore ſhould I uſe any means to avoid impriſonment, when my Suretie hath ſuffered impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment for me? were not means in this caſe frivolous? If Chriſt did <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate</hi> and die for <hi>Iudas</hi> and in his ſtead, then <hi>Iudas</hi> hath ſuffered death by his Suretie Chriſt; what need then is there of <hi>faith</hi> in <hi>Judas,</hi> as a <hi>means</hi> to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:105460:54"/> obtain <hi>application</hi> and freedom from death, after he hath ſuffered death, as by his Suretie? This is as if a <hi>Judge</hi> ſhould hang a man for his offence, and then require him to uſe <hi>means</hi> to free himſelf from death. And ſo much for confutation of this diſtinction, of <hi>Impetration</hi> and <hi>Application.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105460:54"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
